斯坦福大学
Stanford University.
欢迎来到 CS193P
Okay. Well, welcome to CS193P.
这是 2013 至 2014 秋季学期第六讲
This is lecture six, yes, of fall 2013-14.
今天我们会先做一个小小的演示
So, today we are going to have a little demo at the beginning.
我想讲一下
I want to talk to you a little bit
控制器的多态性
about polymorphism with controllers.
也就是说
In other words,
在控制器中使用继承
using inheritance for — in the world of controllers,
有些同学如果对于面向对象编程
and those of you who — for whom object-oriented programming
还不是那么熟练
is not that facile quite yet,
可能会认为
you might be kind of like, oh yeah,
可以生成控制器的子类
I guess I could subclass my controller,
实际上 你确实要生成控制器的子类
and in fact, you do want to subclass your controller,
这很常见
and it’s quite common to subclass controllers.
我讲过
As I said, iOS is kind of
iOS 是基于面向对象编程设计的
all designed around object-oriented programming,
所以你要在系统中各处
so you get to apply object-oriented principles
应用面向对象原理
everywhere in the system,
今天我就要演示这部分内容
so I’m going to show you that today,
能够帮助大家
and that’s to help you a little bit
开始做作业
get you started on your homework,
因为我要布置的作业内容
because what I’m going to ask for your homework
是需要你在 Matchismo 中再添加一个卡牌配对游戏
is for you to add a second card matching game to your Matchismo.
第二个游戏几乎是一样的
Now this second game is almost identical,
游戏规则等都一样
plays by the same rules and everything,
只是用了另外一副卡牌
it really just uses a different deck of cards.
这是主要的不同
Okay, that’s the primary difference,
所以显然你需要更新模型
so you’ll obviously have to update your model
添加另外一副卡牌
to have this extra different deck of cards,
但是游戏的逻辑
but your game playing logic
和控制器的基础部分都是一样的
and the basic part of your controller is the same,
但是我们并不想
but we don’t want to have
让卡牌和控制器相连
playing card wiring into our controller,
所以我们要用继承
so we’re going to use inheritance
创建一副特定卡牌
to create a playing card specific one,
再用一副通用卡牌与其他游戏共享
and then keep a generic one that we can share for the other game,
我们会先来做这个演示
so we’ll show that at the beginning.
然后我们会详细讲解
Then we’re going to dive into
如何为应用添加多个 MVC
how to get multiple MVCs in your application.
换句话说 如何让你的应用实现更多的功能
In other words, how to make your application have more features
不仅局限于一个小小的屏幕
than you can just fit on one little screen.
显然
Okay. And the critical, obviously,
想要构建复杂精细的应用
to building any kind of complicated or sophisticated app
关键在于扩大应用的功能集
is to be able to expand your feature set,
即便是在一个设备上
even though you’re talking about being on a device,
很小的设备 屏幕很小
it’s a small device, it’s a very small screen,
在一屏上只能放置有限个 UI 元素
that limits how much UI you can put on there at a time.
然后 这节课结束之前 我会再演示一个示例
And then I’m going to do a demo towards the end
我会为大家演示
where I’m just going to basically show you –
我说过 我总会先讲讲我们要做什么
I tell you I always talk about what we’re going to do,
然后进行演示
then I demonstrate what we’re going to do,
然后大家在作业中实现讲过的内容
and then you do it for your homework,
今天也是这样的
and that’s exactly going to be true today.
我要接着演示周一的示例 Attributor
So I’ll do the demo with Attributor that we worked on Monday.
增强它的功能 让它具有多个 MVC
We’ll enhance it to have multiple MVCs.
好的 我们先来演示
Okay, so let’s do that demo first.
打开 Matchismo
So, we’re going to take the Matchismo
第三节课最后的示例
as of last — at the end of lecture three,
这个示例是在作业之前演示的
so this is prior to all your homework,
如果你们还记得的话
and if you remember then,
storyboard 是这个样子的
the storyboard looks like this,
只有 12 张卡牌和得分
we just have 12 cards and the score,
非常简单
really, really simple.
有一个卡牌游戏视图控制器
And we have this card game view controller.
这是卡牌游戏视图控制器
Right. This is the card game view controller,
也非常简单
also quite simple.
这是上周的内容 还记得吧
You remember that from last week.
当时我说它有一个问题
The problem with it and I mentioned this at the time,
就是它导入了 PlayingCardDeck
is that it imports PlayingCardDeck.
换句话说
In other words,
这个卡牌游戏控制器
this card game playing controller
算是通用的卡牌游戏机
is pretty generic card game player,
如果在其中增加其他卡牌
and if you put other kinds of cards in there
可能可以正常匹配
it could probably match them,
除了下面的这行代码
except for this one line of code down here
这行代码要求我们导入 PlayingCardDeck
that causes us to drag in PlayingCardDeck
让这个 CardGameViewController 只适用于 PlayingCard 扑克牌
and make this CardGameViewController be playing card specific.
我们要做的很简单
So, what we’re going to do, it’s very simple,
我们要生成一个 CardGameViewController 的子类
we’ re going to create a subclass of this CardGameViewController
只针对扑克牌
that’s specific to playing cards,
然后我们会把所有扑克牌的内容
then we’ll move all the playing card specific stuff
都放到那个子类中
into that subclass,
让当前类整洁和通用
and we’ll keep this one nice and generic.
这个 CardGameViewController 类
This CardGameViewController class
会成为通用的卡牌匹配游戏的视图控制器
is going to be a generic card game matching view controller.
大家明白我要做什么吗
Does that make sense what I’m going to do here?
我们的实现方法是
Okay. So the way we’re going to do that
删掉这行有冲突的代码
is we’re going to get rid of this offending line of code.
这行代码
Okay. This is the line of code
让这个类只针对于扑克牌
that makes this class depend on playing cards,
我要删掉它
and I’m just going to delete it
在 creatDeck 中返回 nil
and return nil here in createDeck.
这样就完成了
Okay, well, that’s done it.
我们变成了通用的卡牌
Okay. We have a generic card,
现在就可以删掉这行了
now I can get rid of that
现在它都是通用的
and it’s all generic,
但是显然这里是有问题的
but obviously, this is going to be a problem
因为没有牌 deck
because now there’s no deck.
对吧 这里会返回 nil
Right. This is going to return nil,
这里会返回 nil
this is going to return nil right here.
这里实际上也会返回 nil
This is actually going to return nil as well,
因为它无法绘制任何卡牌
because it’s not going to be able to draw any cards,
所以是有这个问题的
so this is a problem.
通过修改 把这里改成 nil 以后
So by doing this, by putting this nil right here,
基本上 我们是把 CardGameViewController 类抽象了
we’ve essentially made this class CardGameViewController abstract.
希望大家熟悉面向对象编程
Okay. So, hopefully all of you know enough object-oriented programming
知道抽象这个术语
to know the term abstract.
抽象表示这个类不能被实例化使用
Abstract means that this class cannot be instantiated and used,
它只能用于作为
it’s only useful as a superclass
具体类的超类
for other classes that are concrete –
与之相对的我们叫做具体
what we call concrete.
所以如果我们想对它进行操作的话
Okay. So we need to make a concrete subclass of this
需要创建一个它的具体子类
if we want to do anything with it,
就我自己而言–
and I personally when I –
在 Objective-C 中 没有 abstract 关键词
okay, in objective-c, there’s no abstract keyword
不能直接声明某个类是抽象类
that you can use to specify that this is an abstract class,
你需要在头文件中进行记录
you just have to document it in your header file
标明这个类是抽象类 不能实例化
that this class is abstract, you can’t instantiate.
我还喜欢在其他地方也记录上 甚至在实现文件中
And I also like to document, even on my implementation,
标明哪些方法是抽象的
any methods that basically are abstract.
需要你对其进行重写
Any method that is required that you override this method.
还要注意 所有抽象方法
And also any abstract method,
都应该是公有的
you’ve got to make them public. Okay.
否则具体子类会无法知道
Because otherwise the concrete subclasses won’t be able to know
它们需要实现这些方法
that they’re supposed to implement them.
它们依然可以重写这些方法
Okay. They could still override them
如果有人偷偷告诉它们了
as someone sneakily told them about it,
但是我们不想要偷偷摸摸的
but we don’t want any sneaking around here,
我们想让 createDeck 变成公有的
we want createDeck to be public,
所以我要复制 createDeck 方法
so I’m going to copy createDeck
把它放到公有接口中
and put it in our public interface.
这个抽象注释可以留着
I’m going to leave that thing there that says it’s abstract.
我还要在这里添加一条类的注释
Okay. I’m also going to put a class comment here
写上 抽象类
that says abstract class,
必须按照下面要求实现方法
you know, must implement methods as described below,
或者类似的说明
or something like that,
这样有人看到这个类时
so that when people come to this class
就会知道 这个类是抽象的
they know ooh, this class is abstract.
转到下面
And then we go down here,
通常情况下 我还会在这里添加注释
and then a lot of times I’ll put right here,
比如 protected 受保护的
maybe the word protected
或者 for subclasses 用于超类 之类的
or for subclasses, something like that
以注释来区分两种方法
to kind of make it clear the difference between methods
一种是仅适用于子类的方法
that are just for subclassers,
需要重写之类的
that they’re going to override or something like that,
另一种是公有方法
versus public methods
可能要放到上面这里
which would probably go up here,
是使用这个卡牌游戏控制器的对象要调用的方法
which someone using this card game controller would call.
当然了 这里有一个错误 因为 Deck 没有声明
Okay. So of course, we have an error here because of deck,
所以我们需要导入 Deck
so we have to import deck,
但是这样比导入 PlayingCardDeck 要好多了
but that’s a lot better than importing PlayingCardDeck,
因为目前我们并没有绑定某种卡牌
because we are not now tied to any kind of deck,
任何卡牌都可以
any deck of cards will do. Okay.
明白吗
That make sense?
现在 我们有了这个抽象类
So now that we have this abstract class
它有一个这样的方法 需要实现
that has this method that has to be implemented,
我们创建一个它的具体子类
let’s make that concrete subclass of this
实现 createDeck 方法
that implements createDeck.
和新建类的方法一样
Okay. And we just do that in the same way we create any new class.
选择文件菜单下 新建菜单中的文件
Right. File menu, new file
选择 Objective-C 类
and then we’re going to say we want an objective-c class.
可以在这里指定超类
We can specify the superclass here
输入 CardGameViewController
is gonna be CardGameViewController,
我要叫这个类 PlayingCardGameViewController
and I’m going to call this class PlayingCardGameViewController,
因为这就是它的功能
okay, because that’s what it’s going to do.
它是一个 CardGameViewController
It’s going to be a CardGameViewController,
但是它是具体的
but it’s going to have the concrete thing
它在游戏中使用的是扑克牌
that it is going to play with playing cards.
点击下一步
So, I hit next.
和其他视图控制器放在一个目录下
I’m going to put it in the same place as my other view controller.
出来了
Here it is.
可以看到系统自动添加了一些视图控制器生命周期的代码
You can see a couple of view controller lifecycle stubs in here.
我不需要这些
I don’t need those.
这个方法实际上是指定初始化方法
This is actually the designated initializer.
我也不确定为什么要把它放在这
I’m not sure why it throws that in there,
因为现在我们都从 storyboard 开始执行
because nowadays we pull these things out of storyboard.
我们会用 awakeFromNib viewDidLoad 更好
We would use awakeFromNib, or even better, viewDidLoad. Okay.
所以我们也不需要这个方法
So we don’t want that either.
现在这个具体子类看起来就很整洁了
So we have this nice concrete subclass,
它只需要实现 createDeck
and all this thing needs to do is implement createDeck.
对吧
Okay.
我来实现一下 这里返回–
So I’m going to do that. I’m going to return –
这里确实需要导入 PlayingCardDeck
Okay. Here I do need to import PlayingCardDeck,
但在这里导入没问题
but that’s okay here,
因为这个类就是用于扑克牌的
because that this class is for playing cards.
它就是做这个的
That’s what it’s for,
所以这样做没问题
so I have no problem doing that.
我们再回到下面这里
So let’s go down here –
[PlayingCardDeck alloc] init
PlayingCardDeck alloc init. Okay.
好了 我创建了一个具体子类
Bingo, I’ve created a concrete subclass.
可以用了
It’s ready to go.
如果我回到 storyboard 运行一下
If I were to go back to my storyboard here and run –
我们来运行一下
let’s go ahead and run this.
我们何不在设备上运行一下呢
We’ll do this on the device, why not.
看看会发生什么
See what happens.
有谁可以预测一下运行时会发生什么吗
Can anyone predict what’s going to happen if I run this?
会正常运行吗
Is it going to work?
没人猜一下吗
No guesses?
这里是不能正常运行的
It’s not going to work here,
我看到有人摇头了
I see heads shaking.
应用不能正常运行
No, it’s not going to work.
实际上 它不能正常运行
And in fact, it isn’t going to work,
我们看看它会怎样
and we’ll see what it does.
我试着翻开卡牌
Okay, so I’ m trying to flip cards
现在什么牌都没有 对吧
and all these cards there’s no cards here. Okay.
我刚才创建了具体子类呀
I just made that concrete subclass,
怎么回事 为什么不能用呢
what’s going on? How come it’s not working?
storyboard 还和抽象控制器连在一起
The storyboard’s still tied to the abstract controller.
没错
That’s right.
原因就是 这里的这个 storyboard
So the answer is my storyboard right here,
如果看这里 这个控制器还是抽象的那个
if I look at this, this controller is still the abstract one.
所以它当然不能正常运行
So, it’s actually properly not working.
因为它是抽象的
Okay. Because it is abstract,
没有与之关联的卡牌
it has no cards that are associated with it
没有特定 deck
because it has not deck,
就不能运行
so it doesn’t work.
问题是 我们如何告诉 storyboard
So the question is how do we tell our storyboard
我们想让这个控制器使用具体子类
that we want this controller to use the concrete subclass
而不是抽象超类呢
instead of using that abstract superclass?
答案很简单 我们只要选中它
The answer is very simple, we just select it.
我们可以点击下面的图标进行选中
We can select a controller either by selecting here,
直接点击这里时要注意
be a little careful when you click here, it didn’t–
这样实际上选择的是顶级视图
this actually selected the top level view.
正确选中时 边缘会有蓝色边框
You can see, we need the blue border around the edge.
实际上 在选择元素时
There’s actually a little trick that you can do
可以使用一个小技巧
when you’re selecting things.
让我想想是哪个键
Let’s see if I can remember which one it is.
按住 command 单击 是什么呢 出来了
Go to command, click. Oh, what is that? There is it.
按住 Shift 单击吗 不是 是按住 control 和 shift 键单击
Shift click? No. Okay. Control, shift, click.
当你在某个地方按住 control 和 shift 键单击时
When you go to control, shift, click on something,
会显示出鼠标指针下的所有元素
it will actually show you all the things that are under your mouse.
所以如果我在这里按住 control 和 shift 键单击时
So actually if I control, shift, click here –
对吗 对的
is that what it is? Yeah.
会显示出按钮
Then it’s showing me the button,
它就在鼠标指针下面
which is under right under my mouse,
然后是视图 然后是后面的控制器
then the view, and then the controller behind it,
现在我可以直接选择
and so now I can pick which one of these
我想要选择的元素
I actually meant to select like that. Okay.
不是 control 和 shift 就是 command 和 shift
So I think it’s control, shift, or something command shift.
我老是记不住 记性不好
I can never remember it. Loss of memory.
我的键盘和现在用的这个也不太一样
And my keyboard’s slightly different in this one.
不管怎样 现在我选中了它
So anyway, so now I’ve got it selected,
出现了蓝色边框
it’s got this blue thing around it,
现在我要检查它
so now I’m going to inspect it.
打开检查器
Okay. I’m going to bring up the inspector,
但是我不需要属性检查器
but I don’t want the attributes inspector.
我要检查的是它的标识符
Okay. I’m going to inspect the identity of this thing,
转到标识符检查器
so I go to the identity inspector.
就是这个
That’s this one right here.
在标识符检查器中
Okay. And if you look at the identity inspector,
如果选中了一个控制器
if you have a controller selected,
最上面一项就是这个控制器所属的类
the very top thing is what class is this controller.
可以看到现在是 CardGameViewController
You can see that right now it’s CardGameViewController,
抽象超类
the abstract superclass.
如果我点击这里
So if I click here,
我可以直接输入 PlayingCardViewController
I can either just type PlayingCardViewController,
或者从列表中进行选择
or it could be in the list right here.
滚动一下
So if I scroll around
可以看到 iOS 中的其他类
you can see some other classes that are in iOS,
PlayingCardViewController 在这里
and here’s our PlayingCard one right there.
如果我选择它
If I select that one,
现在再运行时
now when we run,
它就会使用那个具体子类
it’ll be using that concrete subclass,
在游戏中发出扑克牌
which will be dealing out playing cards in our game,
所以应用就又可以正常运行了
so we’re back to having this work.
对吧
Okay.
大家都明白刚才的操作吗
Everybody understand what we did there?
你需要设置控制器的类
Now you’ll have to do this — setting the class of controllers,
如果应用中有多个视图控制器
and this is especially common to have to do
这个操作是特别常见的
when you have multiple view controllers,
当你拖出一个新的视图控制器时
because when you drag out a new view controller,
需要选择它的类
you’ll need to say what class it is.
否则你就不能将输出口和操作
Okay. Otherwise, you won’t be able to hook up your outlets and actions
连接到你的 UIViewController 的子类上了
to your subclass of UIViewController.
好的 这会帮你们开个头
All right. So, that’ll get you started on that,
你们需要再添加一个游戏
and again, you’re going to have another game.
两个游戏
Both of them are going –
你的应用中的两个游戏应该都可以运行
your app is going to be able to play either game.
好的 我要演示的就是这些
All right. That’s it. That’s all I wanted to show there.
我们回来开始讲多个 MVC 的内容
So let’s go back and start talking about multiple MVCs now.
我们为什么需要多个 MVC 呢
Why do we want multiple MVCs?
当然是因为我们可以–
Obviously, so we can have more –
抱歉 有问题吗
Oh, sorry, question.
- 很短的问题 - 说吧
- Just really quickly. – Yeah.
假如说 如果你
So if you — if you, say,
将一个方法与 storyboard 中的某个元素绑定在一起
bind a method to something in the storyboard
和抽象类绑定在一起了 然后你重写了它
and you bind it in the abstract class and then you override it,
是否会自动继承相同的监听者呢
does it automatically inherit the same listener steps?
这是一个好问题
Yeah. So that’s a good question.
问题是 如果我有一个输出口或者操作
The question is, what if I have an outlet or an action
将它连接到了抽象超类中的
that I’ve connected up to some outlet or action
某个输出口或操作上
that’s in your abstract superclass,
然后我将它的类改为了某个具体子类
and then I set the class to be a concrete subclass,
输出口和操作还可以正常使用吗
will all my outlets and actions still work?
是的 它们还会正常工作的
Yes, in fact they will still work.
完全没问题 实际上
They’ll work great, and in fact, if you –
如果你有抽象超类的代码 像这里一样
if you have the code for the abstract superclass like we do here,
实际上 你可以打开 storyboard
you can actually have your storyboard up,
在辅助编辑器中打开抽象超类
and in the assistant editor, open up the abstract superclass
然后连接输出口和操作
and you can wire up outlets and actions,
甚至私有的也可以
okay, even private ones.
抽象超类中的输出口和操作不一定要是私有的
Something doesn’t have to be private in the abstract superclass,
都可以进行连接
the outlets and actions, to wire it up. Okay.
如果辅助编辑器的右侧是自动模式
Now, if you have the right side of your assistant editor set on automatic,
你需要切换到手动
you’ll have to switch it to manual
才能选择抽象超类
to go and pick the abstract superclass,
因为自动模式下显示的是具体子类
because automatic’s going to want to show you the concrete one,
但是和我们这里的示例一样
but like in our example here,
我们不能将卡牌与 PlayingCardViewController 相连接
we can’t wire those cards up to PlayingCardViewController,
因为它没有卡牌按钮对应的输出口
because it doesn’t have that outlet for card buttons.
那是在它的抽象超类中的
That’s in its abstract superclass.
明白吗 所以我们只要打开抽象超类
All right. So we just open up the abstract superclass,
然后进行连接
and we can wire it up.
换句话说 Xcode 很智能 知道继承关系
In other words, Xcode is smart about knowing the inheritance,
允许你与抽象超类
to let you wire up to abstract superclasses,
甚至具体超类相连接
or even concrete superclasses,
即便它们是私有的
and even if they’re private.
输出口和操作是被当作私有内容的
So outlet and action connecting is kind of considered a private thing.
是私有的
All right. It’s kind of a private thing.
不需要都设成公有的 也可以进行连接
You don’t have to make all those public to be able to connect those.
但是调用方法是公有的
But calling methods is something that’s public.
如果你想调用超类中的方法
Okay. If you want to call a method in the superclass,
需要设置为公有的
that needs to be made public,
因为没有保护
because there’s no protected.
明白吗 好问题
Okay. Good question.
好了 接着讲多 MVC
All right so, multiple MVCs.
我们为什么需要多个 MVC 呢
Why we want multiple MVCs?
显然是为了向应用中添加更多内容
Obviously, we can put more stuff in our app.
怎么做呢 其实非常简单
How do we do it? It’s very simple actually,
只要转到对象面板
you just go to the object palette –
就是拖出按钮和滑动条的地方
the same place you drag a button or a slider out of,
从那里拖出一个视图控制器
and you drag out a view controller,
这样拖出时 它是一个通用的视图控制器
and when you drag it out, it’ll be a generic view controller.
也就是说它的类是 UIViewController
In other words, its class will be UIViewController
显然它会是空白的
and it’ll be blank obviously.
然后创建 UIViewController 的子类
Then you go create your subclass of UIViewController.
在我刚才做过的示例中
Okay. In this case, in the demo I just did
我创建了一个已有类的子类
I created a subclass of a class I already had,
但是你可以直接创建 UIViewController 的子类
but you can create this direct subclass of UIViewController,
然后用属性检查器查看它的属性
and then you go and inspect it with the attributes inspector
设置它的类
and you set its class.
就是这样拖入一个新的 MVC
That’s it. That’s how you drag a new MVC in
添加到应用中
and create one for your app.
添加 MVC 很容易
So it’s easy to add MVCs.
添加了 MVC 之后
Now, once you have an MVC added,
就可以向它的视图中添加元素
you can put things in its view,
按钮和标签等等
buttons and labels and stuff,
还可以连接输出口和操作等
and you can hook up outlets and actions and all that stuff
创建第二个 MVC 甚至第三四五个
to create a second MVC, or a third, a fourth, a fifth,
大型应用可能会有 100 个 MVC
or a large app might have 100 MVCs in it,
甚至更多
okay, or more.
添加了这些 MVC 之后
So, you got all these MVCs,
如何展示给用户呢
how do you present them to the use?
有很多方法可以实现
Okay. Well, there’s a number of ways to do it,
但是最基本的方法是
but the fundamental answer is
使用一个视图为其他 MVC 的控制器
you use a controller whose view is other MVCs.
理解一下
Let that sink in a little. Okay.
和所有 MVC 一样 我的这个 MVC 也有一个控制器
So I can have a MVC that has a controller like all MVCs,
而这个控制器的视图是其他 MVC
the view of that controller is other MVCs.
从概念上讲
This is the kind of conceptual way
这就是实现多个 MVC 的方法
we’re going to put multiple MVCs.
今天我要讲两个 iOS 的类
And I’m gonna talk about two classes provided by iOS today,
两个控制器
two controllers,
它们的视图是其他 MVC
whose view is other MVCs.
一个是 UITabBarController 大家都熟悉
One is UITabBarController, you’re used to that.
这种控制器底部有一排选项卡
It’s got tabs along the bottom.
点击不同的选项卡
Every time you click on a tab,
就可以看到不同 MVC 的视图
you can see a different MVC’s view,
再简单不过了
okay, couldn’t be simpler.
这是在屏幕上显示多个 MVC 的最简单的方法
That’s the simplest, you know, way to get multiple MVCs on screen.
然后我会用更多的时间
And then I’m going to spend more time
讲解 UINavigationController
talking about UINavigationController,
这种是在屏幕上显示一个视图
which is the thing where you have something on screen
然后你点击了屏幕上的某个按钮之类的
and you click on a button or something that’s on screen,
一个新视图就会滑进来
and a new view slides in.
然后再点击一次 滑进另一个视图
Okay. And then you maybe click again and another one slides in,
还会出现返回按钮 可以返回
and then there’s a back button and you can back up,
所以可以继续和返回
so go down and back up.
可以深入查看信息或者返回
So when you want to drill down information or back up.
这种稍微复杂些
Okay. So that one’s a little more complicated,
今天大部分时间都会讲解这部分内容
and that’s what I’m going to spend most of the time on today.
还有其他方法可以显示多个 MVC
Now there’s other ways to put multiple MVCs on screen –
iPad 的弹出窗口和模态展示
popovers on iPad and modal presentations.
今天我不会讲
Though I’m not going to talk about those today,
但是后面几周会讲到的
we will cover them all in the next few weeks. Okay.
我想把内容分解成容易理解的小块
I’m just trying to meter this out to you in bite-size chunks.
好的 那我们来讲讲 UINavigationController
All right. So, let’s talk about UINavigationController.
使用 UINavigationController 的最好的示例
So, a great app to look at that uses of UINavigationController
就是日历应用
is the calendar app.
这是显示顶层视图的日历应用
So, here’s the calendar app at its top level.
基本上显示了一整年的日历
You can see it’s basically a year — an entire year.
今天是选中的状态 用红色圆形标出了
Today’s date is selected, the little red in there.
大一点的灰色圆形代表手指
That big gray dot is supposed to be the finger.
在后面的幻灯片中可以看到
You’re going to see it touching various spaces
它点击着不同的地方
as we go through these slides.
UINavigationController 适用于
And we use the UINavigationController
屏幕上有很多内容
when we have a bunch of stuff on screen
而我们想向用户展示更多内容
and we want to show the user more,
更多详细的信息
more detailed, more information.
通常用于这种情况
Okay. Generally, what this navigation –
这很常见
Now, it’s very common to want to do that.
当前显示的是高层级的信息
You’re kind of showing high level information
而你想要展示更多详细的内容
and you want to show more detail, more detail.
在日历应用中
So, the calendar app,
如果手指移到某个日期上 然后点击
if you go over to the day with your finger and you touch,
一个月视图就会滑进来
then a month view slides in.
所有这些都发生在一个 MVC 中
Okay. So all of that happened in a single MVC,
也就是导航控制器对应的 MVC
which was a UINavigationController’s MVC.
紫色或者浅蓝色圈出的这部分
Okay. So the purple or the light blue,
无论大家看起来是什么颜色
whatever color that looks like to you on the screen,
它是 UINavigationController 的视图
that is the view of a UINavigationController.
基础 MVC 明白吗
Based MVC. Okay.
里面有另一个 MVC 的视图
Now, inside there, there’s another MVC’s view,
月视图
the month view.
所以黄色区域是另一个 MVC 的视图
So the little yellow area is another MVC’s view.
在此之前 里面是一个年 MVC 的视图
Okay. And what used to be in there was a year MVC’s view,
又是另外一个 MVC
which was yet another MVC.
可以看到它们是如何嵌入的
Okay. So you can see how it’s imbedded.
而且不只是嵌入
And not only is it embedded,
导航控制器还控制着自己的 UI
but the navigation controller is kind of controlling its own UI,
根据嵌入内容的不同而变化
based on what happens to be embedded at the time.
我可以在某一天上点击
And so, I could click on the day
日视图就会进来 这里就换成了日 MVC
and a day view comes in, so this is a day MVC.
所以这里我们看到了四个 MVC
So this is four MVCs we’ve seen here.
最外层的导航控制器是一个
The surrounding navigation controller one,
显示出来的年月日
and now three separate year, month and day MVCs
分别是三个 MVC
that are being shown in here.
明白吗
Okay.
我们来看一下
So let’s take a look –
当然了 我们还可以继续点击
Of course, we can click again
打开事件详情页面
and now get the details for an event,
所以这里我们看到了五个 MVC
so there’s five MVCs that we’ve seen.
我们来看一下这个导航控制器的组成部分
So let’s look at the components of this UINavigationController.
顶部有浅灰色的一栏
So at the top, there’s this light gray bar
不管下面显示的是哪个 MVC
that stayed on the screen, you notice,
它始终都显示在屏幕上
for all of the MVCs as they come swiping in.
但是不同 MVC 出现时 它会略微变化
Okay. But it changed slightly as they all swiped in,
我们来看看它的组成部分
so let’s look at all the parts.
这个导航栏包括三个主要部分
There’s three major parts there of that navigation bar.
首先是标题 Event Details 事件详情
First is the title, okay, Event Details.
你会发现显示月和日时
You’ll notice that the month and the day –
是没有标题的
actually, I don’t think they even had titles,
这是合理的
which is perfectly legal.
这里会显示事件详情
This says Event Detail because the navigation controller
是因为导航控制器询问嵌入的控制器
is basically asking the embedded controller，
也就是日历事件 MVC
the calendar event MVC，
你的标题是什么
what’s your title,
得到它的标题之后 将它显示在顶部
and then it gets that and it puts that at the top.
也可以在 storyboard 中设置这个标题
You can also set that title in your storyboard if you want to.
明白吧
Okay.
这个标题
But it’s associated –
和内部显示的内容有关
that title’s associated with what’s inside，
根据导航控制器中嵌入 MVC 的不同
what’s embedded in the navigation controller
在滑进不同视图时改变标题
and it changes as things slide in.
明白吧
Okay.
右边这里还有按钮
Also, we have the buttons on the right here.
现在只有一个 Edit 编辑按钮
So, there’s only one button here — Edit,
但是如果大家还记得
but if you remember back to the month and day,
在月和日页面中有两个按钮
there were actually two buttons,
可能有一个加号按钮 用来增加事件
like a little plus sign to add an event maybe,
有一个放大镜用来搜索等等
and a little magnifying glass to search, things like that.
所以这里其实可以放多个按钮
So you can actually have multiple buttons here,
这也就是为什么它是一个 NSArray
that’s why it’s an NSArray.
这些按钮并不是 UIButton
Now, these buttons are not UIButtons,
它们是 UIBarButtonItem
they’re UIBarButtonItems.
类似于轻量级的按钮
Okay. Kind of lightweight buttons.
导航控制器如果想要确定显示哪个按钮
And the navigation controller figures out which one to put there
需要向嵌入的视图请求一个对象 叫做 navigationItem
by asking the embedded view for an object called a navigationItem,
所有 UIViewController 都有这个 navigationItem 属性
so all UIViewControllers have this property navigationItem,
返回的对象中
and it returns this object that has some stuff in there
包括 rightBarButtonItems 等
like rightBarButtonItems,
rightBarButtonItem 是个数组
which is an array. Okay.
大家明白这个属性表示法吗
Everybody understand the property notation I’m using there?
navigationItem.rightBarButtonItems
navigationItem dot rightBarButtonItems.
这是从嵌入的视图中得到的
I’m getting that from the embedded view,
日视图 月视图等等
you know, the day view, or the month view or whatever.
根据它们决定上面出现的按钮
That’s what’s determining the buttons that are up there.
左边的返回按钮
This back button over here on the left,
如果我点击它
if I click that button,
就会返回到上一个页面
it’s going to go back to the last thing that was there,
在这个示例中 会回到日视图
which in this case was the day view. All right.
这是由 UINavigationController 自动实现的
And that’s automatically done by UINavigationController,
而按钮上显示的单词
and the word it’s going to use there is,
如果放得下的话
if it’ll fit,
就是上一个 MVC 的标题
the title of the previous MVC.
这里是 Day 可以放得下
So this case is day, works, it fits.
也可以进行设置
It can also be set,
因为我并不知道日 MVC
because I don’t know that the day MVC
真的有一个标题 Day
actually had a title that said day,
也许有 但我不知道
might have, but I don’t think so,
所以这里也可以设置
so it can be set.
如果放不下的话 就会直接显示 Back 返回
Also if it doesn’t fit, it’ll just say the word back.
有时也会遇到这种情况
Okay. So you’ll see that sometimes.
但是用户知道左上角是用来返回的
But the user knows that upper left hand corner is how they go back,
他们进入下面的层级后 可以返回
so they drill down, they can go back.
如果我点击那个返回按钮
And if I click on that back button,
显然我会返回到日视图
obviously, I’m going to go back to the day.
如果我再点击一下
If I click again,
就会返回到月视图
I’m going back to the month.
好的 这就是返回按钮
All right. So that’s the back button.
而在底部
Now down at the bottom,
也有一小条灰色栏
you see there’s a little light gray bar there.
它并不是总显示在那里的
That’s not always there.
日历事件 MVC 中就没有这一栏
That wasn’t there on the calendar event MVC, by the way.
这只是一些 UIBarButtonItems
This is just a bunch of UIBarButtonItems
只有在嵌入的 MVC 视图需要时
that again, the navigation controller only displays
导航控制器才会显示这一栏
if the embedded MVC’s view says that it wants them.
对应着另外一个属性 叫做 toolbarItems
Okay. And there’s another property for that called toolbarItems,
导航控制器调用嵌入视图控制器的
so you call — the navigation controller calls toolbarItems
toolbarItems 属性
on the embedded view controller,
会得到一个 UIBarButtonItem 的 NSArray
and it returns an NSArray of UIBarButtonItems
然后将它们显示在底部
and it puts them in the bottom.
如果嵌入的视图控制器
And if the embedded view controller
不需要在底部显示栏按钮
doesn’t want any bar buttons at the bottom,
导航控制器就不会显示灰色这栏
then it just animates that gray thing away
如果转到需要显示底部栏按钮的视图控制器
and then animates it back,
会再显示出这一栏
if you navigate it back to one that does.
大家都明白它的组成部分了吗
So everyone understand the components
UINavigationController 的组成部分
of UINavigationController?
现在我们讲讲它是如何工作的
Okay. So now let’s talk about how this thing works.
我们知道它的组成部分
We know the parts of it.
我从 MVC 的角度讲一下
I’m going to do this kind of in a MVC like view of this.
这里我有一个 MVC
So, here I have an MVC. Right.
和第一节课用到的是一样的 记得吧
You recognize this from the very first lecture. Right.
假设我有很多功能 屏幕上放不下
And let’s say I have more features than I can fit onscreen.
需要在屏幕上显示更多的视图和按钮等等
So got extra views and buttons and stuff I want to put on screen,
但就是放不下
but they just won’t fit.
我该怎么做呢
Okay. So what do I do?
像我刚才说过的 我们创建第二个 MVC
Well, like I said, we create a second MVC.
这里有很重要的一点需要理解
Now, what’s really important to understand here
就是 MVC 需要各自独立
is that MVCs need to be independent.
所以第二个 MVC 需要封装一些功能
Okay. So this second MVC has to encapsulate some amount of functionality
需要能够创建好
and it has to be able to be set up,
准备出现在屏幕上
prepared to be onscreen,
然后能够独自运行
and then it has to be able to run by itself.
为什么呢
Okay. Why is that?
因为这个 MVC
That’s because this MVC
是要作为另一个 MVC 的视图
is gonna serve as the view of another MVC.
还记得我们在讲 MVC 时讲过
And remember from the MVC discussion,
视图并不能向控制器发送消息
that the views can’t really talk back to their controllers.
控制器可以向视图发送消息
The controller can talk to the view.
视图想要向控制器发回消息只有一种方法
The only way the view can talk back
就是通过不可视结构化通信
is by this blind structured communication
比如目标操作等等
like target action and things like that.
有一种不可视结构化通信方法
And there is blind structure communication –
是我们讲过的委托
delegation, basically, we talked about,
可以实现作为视图的 MVC 向控制器发送消息
for an MVC — part of a view to talk back,
但是这种方法就复杂多了
but it’s much more complicated,
通常情况下我们尽量不用它
and usually we try to avoid it.
我们真正想要的是设置好这个 MVC 让它独自运行
We really want to set this MVC up and have it live on its own.
这在尝试和设计时非常重要
Okay. It’s really important to try and design,
是面向对象编程的一部分
it’s really just part of object-oriented programming
进行封装
to encapsulate things.
这个 MVC 希望被封装
So this MVC wants to be encapsulated.
希望能自力更生
It wants to have its own life. Okay.
我们接下来讲讲
So, let’s talk about then
UINavigationController 是如何加进来的
how UINavigationController comes into this.
如果第二个 MVC 想要展示的内容
If the second MVC, what is wants to show,
是第一个 MVC 的详细信息
is more detail of the first MVC,
那 UINavigationController 很适合这种情况
then a UINavigationController is appropriate.
UINavigationController 看起来是这样的
All right. A UINavigationController looks like this.
它是一个 MVC
It’s an MVC,
它的控制器是 UINavigationController
its controller is the UINavigationController,
它的视图是这个白色的长方形
its view is this kind of white rectangular thing
顶部有一条灰色栏
with the gray bar at the top,
底部也可能有一条灰色栏
and possibly a gray bar at the bottom,
它有一个 rootViewController 根视图控制器
and it includes a rootViewController,
是一个特殊的输出口
which is a special outlet
指向另一个 MVC 的控制器
that comes out that points to the controller of the MVC
而这个 MVC 会在应用开始运行时显示在导航控制器中
that’s going to appear in the navigation controller when it starts up,
就是它的根视图控制器
its root view controller.
如果将这个 MVC 设为根视图控制器
Okay. So when you set that to be this MVC,
导航控制器看起来就会是这样的
the navigation controller is going to look like this.
它会将根视图控制器 MVC 的视图
It’s gonna put the view of that root view controller’s MVC into –
嵌入它的视图中
embedded inside of its view.
大家都明白吗
Right. Everyone understand that?
如果这个视图中或者顶栏中
Okay. Now, if you then have some button or something
有一些按钮之类的
inside this view or maybe in the bar at the top
用来提供更多详细信息
that wants to give that more detail
通过另外一个 MVC 来展示
and have this other MVC provides,
点击了那个按钮之后
you click on that button
就会滑入另一个 MVC 的视图
and it slides in the view for this other MVC,
可以看到 还会在左上角添加返回按钮
okay, and puts a back button there as you see.
现在 当 MVC
Now again, when the MVC –
当导航控制器处于当前状态时
when the navigation controller’s in this state,
左侧的 MVC 最好毫无声息
okay, the MVC that’s on the left kind of wants to be quite.
它不希望做任何操作
It doesn’t want to be doing anything. Okay.
现在它并没有参与进来
It’s not really involved right now.
而右侧的 MVC 完全处于控制状态
Then MVC on the right is completely in control.
所以它要做的所有事情
Okay. And so it should be doing everything it’s doing
都应该可以自己独立完成
on its own, independently.
当然 那个小小的返回按钮
Now of course, that little back button
会在 MVC 切换时自动出现
which automatically appears when you do this –
我们会讲到这部分的
we’re going to talk about, by the way,
会讲到如何转到另一个 MVC
how to make this happen, to go to another MVC.
当你点击这个小返回按钮时
This little back button, when you press it,
显然它会移回到原来的 MVC
it’s obviously just going to move back to the original one,
这时这个 MVC 又处于活动状态了
then this MVC is now live again.
当我们点击返回按钮时
What happened to the MVC on the right
右侧的 MVC 会发生什么呢
when we clicked the back button?
答案是 它会被从堆中释放
The answer is, it got de-allocated from the heap.
这也是需要理解的重要的一点
Okay. This is an important thing to understand as well.
右侧的那个 MVC
Okay. That MVC on the right
从 storyboard 中化冻 显示在屏幕上
got unfreeze-dried from the storyboard when we put it onscreen,
当它离开屏幕时 会被释放
and when it went back off screen, it got de-allocated.
每次我们向 UINavigationController 上
Okay. Every time we push a new thing
压入新 MVC 时
onto a UINavigationController,
都是从 storyboard 中新建一个
we’re creating a new one from the storyboard.
在堆中新实例化一个
Okay. We’re instantiating a new one in the heap,
返回之后 它就会消失
and every time we go back and it goes away,
被释放了
it’s de-allocated.
所以这些 MVC 需要知道如何变为活动状态
So these MVCs need to know how to come to life,
准备出现在屏幕上 做要做的事情
be prepared to come onscreen, do what they do,
完成之后 保存工作进度
finish what they’ve done, save whatever work it is,
然后离开
and then just go away.
就是这种模式
Okay. That is the modal.
有些人可能会对此很困惑
Some people will be confused by that.
自己的数据呢 都没了
You’ll think oh, what happened to all my data, it’s gone.
因为它被释放了 对吧
Well, because it got de-allocated, all right,
返回时就会进行这样的操作
because that’s what happens when you do back.
所以如果某些数据需要继续使用
Okay. So if there’s any data in there that needs to stay,
你就需要在某处对它进行保存
you need to save it somewhere.
可以通过反向通信
Okay. And you could do it by communicating back
向将你压进来的那个 MVC 发送消息来实现
to the MVC that pushed you onscreen,
但是必须借助不可视结构化通信
but you have to do it with that blind structured communication.
后面的课程中会讲到
And we’ll do that later in the quarter. Okay.
反正这次作业用不到
You won’t have to do that for this assignment whatsoever.
从根本上说 就是这样工作的
Okay. So, that’s basically how it works.
现在我们再讲一下压入操作
Now, let’s talk a little bit about that pushing.
如何让第二个 MVC 出现在屏幕上呢
How do we make a second MVC appear on screen?
如何让它滑入呢
How do we make it do that sliding in thing?
答案是使用 segue
Well, the answer is we use what’s called a segue.
segue 是这节课需要理解的非常重要的内容
Okay. Segues are very important to understand in this class.
segue 是用来从一个 MVC
A segue is just when you’re going to move or segue,
移动或 segue 跳转到另一个 MVC
from one MVC to another.
segue 的作用就是这样
Okay. That’s what a segue’s about
UINavigationController 中用到的 segue
and the segue that’s involved in a UINavigationController
叫做 push 类型 segue
is called a push segue.
可以把导航控制器看作是
We kind of think of the navigation controller as
在最前面压入一个新的 MVC
we push a new MVC into the front,
可能会再压入一个
and maybe push another one,
然后点击返回按钮后
and then we pop back and pop back
再逐一弹出回去
when we hit the back button.
我们用的是这个术语
Okay. That’s the terminology that we use.
但是它叫做 push 类型 segue
But it’s called a push segue.
我们先来讲一下如何设置一个 push 类型 segue
So, let me talk about how to set up a push segue first,
然后再演示如何将全部内容
and then we’ll show you how to put the whole thing
放入一个导航控制器中
into a navigation controller.
所以这里分为两个步骤
Okay. So that’s the two-step process here.
现在我们只有一个 MVC
All right. So we’ve only had the single MVC.
我再来快速演示一下 如何新建一个 MVC
Let’s show briefly again, how you create a new one.
只要从对象面板拖拽出一个 UIViewController
I’m just going to drag a UIViewController out of the object pallet.
就是这样
It appears like that.
然后转到标识符检查器
Then I’m going to go up to the identity inspector,
不是属性检查器 而是标识符检查器
not the attributes inspector, the identity inspector,
将这里的类选项
and I’m going to set the class
设置成为我之前通过新建文件创建的类
to be whatever class I’ve created with file, new file,
或者也可能已经有那个类了
or I might have that class lying around,
因为在 storyboard 中很有可能会出现
because it’s very possible in a storyboard
多个场景使用同一个控制器的情况
to have multiple of these scenes that use the same controller,
如果是在不同环境中展示相同的内容
if you’re displaying the same thing in different environments,
都可以的 完全没问题
so whatever. It’s perfectly fine.
很容易忘记在这里设置类
It’s a very common mistake to forget to do this.
你可能会来问我
All right. You end up coming to office hours and saying
我拖出了新的视图控制器
ah, I put this — I dragged out my new view controller,
新建了视图控制器类
I created my new view controller class,
但是我却不能连接输出口或者操作
but I can’t hook up any of the outlets or actions.
因为你忘记设置类了
Well, because you forgot to set the class.
操作很简单 但是也很容易忘记
Okay. Simple thing to do, but simple to forget as well.
我敢肯定在这门课上至少会出现一次
I’m sure at least one time in a demo in this class in lecture,
我也忘了做这个操作
I’ll forget to do that too,
到时候就靠大家提醒我不要忘了这一步了 好吗
so I’m relying on you to say oh, don’t forget to set the class. Okay.
设置好类之后
So once you’ve set the class,
现在就有了这两个 MVC 控制器不同
now you have these two MVCs with different controllers.
现在它们都没有视图
Okay. There’s no view in either of these right now.
这个白色小长方形 我们叫做 scene 场景
We call this, one of these little rectangular things, a scene,
是在 storyboard 中的
okay, in the storyboard.
如果我说场景
If you hear me use the word scene,
就表示一个控制器
I just mean a combination of a controller
和一个特别创建的视图的组合
and a particular view that we’ve built.
这叫做场景
Okay. So that’s called a scene.
现在我要做的操作是
Okay. So, what we’re going to do now
拖出一个按钮 放到左边的场景中
is I’m going to drag a button into the left scene,
当点击那个按钮时
and when we click that button,
它会滑进 UINavigationController 中
it’s going to slide it in in a UINavigationController.
会压入进去
Okay. It’s going to push it.
所以我们要把按钮放到左边
So we’re going to put that button in the left,
然后创建一个连接到右边的 push 类型 segue
and we’re going to create a push segue to the right.
把按钮放到那里
So let’s put the button there.
我们只要把它放在中间
All right. We’re just gonna drop it right in the middle there.
不用编辑标题什么的
I’m not going to change the title or anything.
创建 segue 的方法就是按住 control 键进行拖拽
To make it segue all I do — control drag.
Xcode 中就是要按住 control 键进行拖拽
Right. That’s what we do in Xcode, we control drag.
只要从 segue 开始的地方按住 control 键
So you just control drag from the thing you want to start the segue
拖动至想要 segue 到的视图控制器上
over to the view controller you want it to segue to.
松开鼠标后
Okay. When you let go of the mouse,
就会出现这个黑色的列表
it’s going to put this little black thing up
询问你想要什么类型的 segue
and ask what kind of segue do you want here,
在当前情况下 只有三种可用
and in this context, there’s only three that make sense –
push 类型 适用于导航控制器
push, which would be navigation controller one.
modal 类型 我们稍后会讲到
Modal, which we’ll talk about later,
这种类型的 segue 会接管屏幕
which is take over the screen segue.
我放在后面讲 因为它有可能会被滥用
I teach you that late because that can be abused.
我们并不想过多地使用这种类型
Okay. We don’t want to do that too much.
custom 类型允许你创建自己的 segue
And then custom create your own segues.
我们这门课上不会讲到它的
We’re not even going to talk about that in this class,
非常少见
that’s so rare.
点击 push 之后
All right. So I click push
MVC 之间会出现这个小图标
and it puts this little thing in between my MVCs.
看到这个圆形图标了吗
You see that little round thing?
它代表 segue
That’s a segue.
它是可以点击的
Okay. And this is a clickable thing.
实际上 你也需要点击它
In fact, you’re going to need to click on it,
因为当你点击它后
because when you click on it
转到属性检查器
and you go to the attributes inspector,
可以看到有两项
you’ll see that it has two things actually,
一项是 segue 类型 这里是 push
one is the type of segue, which is push,
它的上面是标识符
but above that, it has this identifier.
我把这个 segue 叫做 Do Something 做某事
Okay. And I call this segue the Do Something segue.
为什么要在这里加上这个标识符
Now why do I need to put this identifier here?
实际上 这个标识符差不多是必须设置的
And actually, it’s pretty much mandatory to put something here.
因为我需要在代码中标识出这个 segue
And the reason is that I need to identify this segue in my code.
这是一个连接点
Okay. This is the link,
有人可能会认为它很脆弱
tenuous as one might argue it is,
它是 Xcode 和你的代码间
between Xcode and your code,
关于 segue 的连接点
when it comes to a segue.
基本上 我们都会命名 segue
Okay. We essentially name these segues,
赋予它们标识符字符串
we give them identifier strings
然后就可以在代码中使用
and in our code we can refer to them.
下面的一些幻灯片中
And you’ll see in a few slides here,
将会看到在代码中什么地方用到了它们
where in our code we refer to this,
命名 segue 是非常重要的
but it’s very important to do that.
这是另外一件
Okay. Another common thing –
容易忘记的事情
this is a common thing to forget.
你创建了一个 segue
You create a segue,
转到代码才发现自己忘记命名了
you go to your code, and you’re like oh, oops,
最后还得回到 Xcode 中对它命名
and then you end up having to go back to Xcode and naming it.
这个操作不大可能会过了很久才发现
This one you’re less likely to get very far without remembering to go back,
但依旧是经常会忘记的操作
but it’s still something that’s commonly forgotten.
我们要将这个 segue 叫做 Do Something
All right. So, we’re gonna call this segue the Do Something segue.
命名时通常会选择具有描述性的标识符
Usually you want to pick an identifier that describes in some –
就像变量名描述变量一样
you know, just like a variable name would describe,
表明它要做什么
what’s going on here.
这是一个通用的示例
So this is a generic example,
点击按钮后 我们会做某事
so when we click that button, we’re going to do something,
所以我叫它 Do Something 做某事
so I called it Do Something,
但是你们也许会选一个更好的名字
but you probably want to pick a better name than Do Something.
不那么通用的名字
That’s a little generic. Okay.
但是这里有个问题
Okay. So, there’s a problem here though.
如果现在这样运行应用
If I were to run my application in this state,
是不会正常运行的
it would not work.
点击那个按钮不会发生 segue 跳转
Okay. Clicking that button would not segue.
为什么呢
Why is that?
因为这些 MVC 需要放在导航控制器中
Because this whole thing has to be in a navigation controller.
这有两个 MVC
Right. These two MVCs –
我需要第三个 MVC
I need a third MVC,
即它们所在的导航控制器
which is the navigation controller they’re in.
我们讲讲如何实现
So, let’s talk about how to do that.
非常简单
It’s very simple.
选择想要的根视图控制器
You pick which one of these you want to be the root view controller,
导航控制器的根视图控制器
all right, of the navigation controller,
然后打开编辑器菜单选择嵌入导航控制器
and you go to the editor menu and you say embed in navigation controller.
我选择了左边这个
So I picked the one on the left,
可以看到它周围的深蓝色边框
you see it’s got the dark blue line around it.
选择菜单中的嵌入 > 导航控制器
I say embed in navigation controller,
这样做之后
and when I do that, boom,
就会创建一个导航控制器
it’s going to create a navigation controller,
所以现在 storyboard 中有三个 MVC
so now I have three MVCs in this storyboard. Three.
导航控制器在左边
I’ve got the navigation controller on the left,
另外两个在右边
and then I’ve got my two other ones on the right. Okay.
最左边的小箭头
And the little arrow on the very left,
看到那个从左边指出来的箭头了吗
do you see that arrow that kind of points in from the left?
它代表应用开始运行时
That is where — that’s the MVC that’s going to be onscreen
将显示在屏幕上的 MVC
when your application launches.
那个小箭头其实可以被拾取和移动
And that little arrow can actually be picked up and moved around.
只要拾取它 移动到你想要的 MVC 上
Just pick it up and drop it on any MVC you want.
那个 MVC 就会成为应用开始运行时的第一个 MVC
That’s going to be the MVC when you start.
这个箭头原来指向的是
Now it used to be pointing at the MVC
中间有 Button 单词的那个 MVC
that has the word button in there in the middle,
但是我将它嵌入到导航控制器中以后
but as soon as I embedded it in a navigation controller
它就会自动移出来 指向导航控制器
it automatically moved it out to the navigation controller.
将箭头指向导航控制器内的 MVC
It would never make sense to have a little arrow
完全没有意义
pointing to an MVC that’s inside a navigation controller.
这样的意思不是说打开导航控制器
Okay. Because that doesn’t mean bring up the navigation controller
让这个 MVC 成为它的根视图控制器
and have this be the root view controller.
这样的意思很奇怪
That would just mean something strange.
我也不知道为什么会允许这样的操作
I’m not even sure why it’s going to allow that,
但这样是不能正常运行的
but it wouldn’t work.
应用开始运行时不会出现导航控制器
When it came up there would be no navigation controller,
因为你绕过了它
because you’d be bypassing the navigation controller.
但是你可以拖动箭头 指向选项卡栏控制器
So — but you can drag that little arrow to a tab bar controller,
有时为了测试 可以将箭头指向一个视图控制器
or sometimes in testing, it’s nice to move them to a view controller
让应用从它开始运行
and just say oh, just start with this view controller,
因为这些视图控制器应该是可以独立运行的
because remember these view controllers are supposed to stand on their own,
所以可以在测试时将开始箭头指向它们
so you can sometimes drag it to startup for testing
测试完成再移回去
and then drag it back.
今天如果有时间的话
In fact, I’ll try to do that,
我会演示一下
if we have time in the demo today. Okay.
第二个小圆形图标
The second little thing there,
看起来像是一个 segue 但其实不是
that looks like a segue, but it’s not actually.
它只用于展示导航控制器
That’s actually just showing you the root view controller connection
与根视图控制器之间的连接关系
from the navigation controller. Okay.
当出现这个图标
When you see the little –
看起来像是一条线两个点
kind of it looks like a line with two dots in there
代表它是输出口类型的连接 而不是 segue
that means it’s a kind of an outlet type of connection not a segue.
二者很相似 但是你不能检查它
Looks very similar, but you can’t inspect it,
不能设置它的标识符
you can’t set an identifier.
这里都不需要
None of that’s necessary here.
它只是用来表示这个连接
It’s just showing you that connection.
但这个是 segue
But this one, that is the segue,
是几张幻灯片前我们按住 control 键拖拽出的
the thing that we control dragged a few slides ago.
如果我点击它
If I click on that,
会显示它的标识符 Do Something 等等
it would say identifier Do Something, etcetera,
注意 所有场景
and notice that all — every single one of the scenes
当前导航控制器中的所有场景
that is now inside this navigation controller –
不只是根视图控制器
not just the root view controller,
所有能过通过 push 类型 segue 导航到的场景
but everything it can navigate to with push segues,
在 Xcode 中都在顶部添加了导航栏
gets a bar on the top in Xcode.
这样可以方便你布局 UI
And that’s so you can lay out your UI nicely,
布局时考虑到那个导航栏始终都会出现在场景顶部
knowing that that bar is always going to be on top of that scene,
因为它在导航控制器中
because this thing is inside a navigation controller.
如果你要添加 toolbarItems
Okay. And if you’re adding toolbarItems things,
也会在顶部出现一栏
then you’ll have a bar on the bottom as well.
如果这些场景都在选项卡栏控制器中
If this was all inside a tab bar controller,
这是可以的 你们的作业中就要这么做
which is legal and which you’re going to be doing for your homework,
这种情况会在底部出现一条选项卡栏
then it would also have a bar for the tab bar,
UI 会变短
and so the UI would be squinching down
你需要调整 UI 以适应这种布局
as you have to make your UI fit.
下周或者下下周
And again, next week or the week after,
也许我们会讲到自动布局
I guess, we’re going to talk about autolayout,
通过它 可以在这些元素
which is a way as these things are appearing or disappearing,
这些顶部栏和底部栏出现消失时
these bars on the top and bottom,
自动对 UI 进行调整
to automatically have that stuff rearrange,
但是目前你需要手动调整
but for now you’re going to have to manually do it. Okay.
如果需要 你可以在栏标题上双击
You can double click on the title in these bars
设置标题
and set the title if you want,
否则这里显示的就是当前场景视图控制器的标题
or it’ll ask the view controller that’s at that scene for its title,
只要使用标题属性就可以得到
just using the title property,
此外 如果你还想在顶部添加按钮
and you can also — if you wanted to add a button to the top,
还记得日历顶部的按钮吗 比如搜索按钮
remember the calendar has like the search button,
添加和编辑按钮
and the add button, and the edit button at the top.
方法是直接拖出一个按钮放在这里
The way you do that is you just drag a button in,
但是这里不要用 UIButton
but don’t use UIButton here.
不然你会在拖拽 UIButton 时受挫的
Okay. Or you’ll be frustrated if you try to drag UIButton.
会疑惑 为什么 UIButton 不能放到那里呢
It’s like ah, how come the UIButton won’t go there?
因为我们要用 UIBarButtonItem
And that’s because we use UIBarButtonItem,
它是比较轻量级的
which is kind of a lighter weight one.
滚动到差不多面板最底部
You scroll down almost to the bottom of the pallet
就能看到这个 Bar Button Item 栏按钮项
you’ll see this thing — Bar Button Item.
将它拖出 可以看到它会放到那里
You drag that out, you’ll see that it will drop there
松开鼠标之后
and when you let it go,
就出现了一个按钮 叫做 Item
now you have a button there called item.
这个按钮只会在一种情况下出现
That button will only appear
就是这个中间有 Button 按钮的 MVC
when this MVC — the one that has button in the middle of it,
当前在导航控制器中可见的时候
is the currently visible thing in the navigation controller.
只有这时 Item 按钮才会出现
That’s the only time the item will appear.
这里完全可以
Okay. And it is perfectly legal to,
不使用从 Button 到下一个 MVC 的 segue
instead of having our segue go from button to the next one,
可以从 Item 按钮按住 control 键拖动到下一个 MVC
we could control drag from that item to the next one.
我会在示例中为大家演示
In fact, I’ll do that in the demo just to show you.
所以顶部的这个 Item 按钮
Okay. So that item button at the top
可以作为 segue 的起点
is allowed to be a source of segueing.
实际上这很常见
In fact, it very commonly is.
好了 我们讲完了如何压入 MVC
All right. Okay. So, we talked about pushing this stuff on.
让它显示在屏幕上
Okay. That’s how you get something to appear –
方法是通过 push 类型 segue
the segue, push segue.
如何离开屏幕呢
How about coming off?
通常情况下是通过用户点击返回按钮
Well normally, things are coming off by a user hitting the back button,
这个时候就应该离开屏幕了
and that’s when you want it to happen.
你希望用户能够感觉
You want the user to feel in control
自己控制着深入细节和返回的操作
of their diving down for detail and coming back,
所以那个返回按钮需要起作用
so you’ll want that back button to work.
但在一些情况中
But there are a few times
需要通过编程方式实现
when it makes sense to programmatically do it
有一个例子是 假设
and one example is, let’s say,
你打开详情页 显示了某条雇员记录
you dive down and you’re showing some employee record,
里面有一个删除按钮
and a button in there is delete,
表示删除这位雇员
meaning delete this employee.
如果你点击了那个删除按钮
Well if you hit that delete button,
就没有理由再留在这个页面了
it doesn’t make any sense to be here anymore,
因为那位雇员没有了
because that employee is gone,
所以你需要返回
so you want to go back.
回到上一级
Okay. You want to go back to the previous level,
所以你可以调用 UINavigationController 中的这个方法
and so you can call this method in UINavigationController
叫做 popViewControllerAnimated
called popViewControllerAnimated.
而且动画参数几乎全部都是 YES
We almost always specify yes, by the way, in animation.
你并不希望 UI 跳来跳去
You don’t want your UI jumping around.
你希望页面能够滑入 渐入等等
You want things sliding in and fading in and stuff like that,
下面几周中
and we’re going to talk a lot about animation
我们会讲到很多动画的内容
in the next couple weeks of your own stuff.
你可能会问
But you might ask,
如何得到当前 UINavigationController
how do I get ahold of my UINavigationController
向它发送这个消息呢
to send it this message
这部分都是现成的 非常好用
and an awesome thing about this way is all set up is,
如果你是一个视图控制器
if you are a view controller
在一个导航控制器中
and you are inside a navigation controller –
在它堆中的某个地方
anywhere on its stack,
你可以得到自己的一个属性
you can get the property on yourself
叫做 navigationController
called navigationController
它会返回你所在的导航控制器
and it will return you the navigation controller you’re in.
明白吗
Does that make sense?
如果你不在导航控制器中
If you’re not in a navigation controller,
它就会直接返回 nil
it’ll just return nil,
MVC 可以在很多环境中运行
and it’s perfectly reasonable to have MVCs
可以在导航控制器中运行
that can live in a navigation controller,
可以在选项卡栏控制器中运行
or live in a tab bar controller,
或者是在选项卡栏控制器中的导航控制器中
or live in a navigation controller that’s inside a tab bar controller,
或者是自己独立运行
or live on their own,
或者是在模态情景下运行等等
or live in a modal situation, whatever.
我们希望 MVC 可以运行于各种地方
You want to have MVCs that are flexible about where they live,
所以有时这里会返回 nil
so sometimes this’ll return nil,
你可能要判断一下 如果在导航控制器中就弹出
and you might say, if I’m in a navigation controller then pop.
如果不在 就做些别的
If I’m not then, you know, do something else.
明白吧
All right.
self.navigationController 是控制器中很好用的属性
So, self dot navigationController is a good thing to know inside a controller.
能告诉你当前所在的视图控制器
It tells you the view controller you’re in.
此外还有 self.tabBarController
There’s also self dot tabBarController.
可以告诉你当前所在的选项卡栏控制器
You can find out the tab bar controller you’re in,
但是几乎用不到
although you almost never need that,
但 navigationController 是需要的
but navigationController you do,
如果你要弹出或做其他操作的时候
if you’re going to pop or do some other things.
除了 push 类型 还有什么类型的 segue 呢
What other segues are there besides push?
我说到了 modal 和 popover
I mentioned the modal and popover,
还有一个 replace
there’s also a replace,
仅适用于 iPad 应用
which is an iPad only thing,
还有 custom 类型
and there’s custom ones.
后面几节课中我们会讲到 iPad 的内容
We’ll talk about iPad stuff in a few lectures,
到时就会讲到这些类型
and we’ll cover all that then,
再说一遍 我们要把 modal 放在后面讲解
and again, we’ll talk about modal later,
因为它很容易被滥用
because it’s kind of easily abused.
好的 现在我们讲一下 segue 时
Okay. So, now let’s talk about what happens in code
代码中会发生什么
when a segue happens.
我们已经知道屏幕上会发生什么了
We already know what happens on screen,
也就是这个新的 MVC 滑进来
which is this new MVC slides in.
从月份滑到日期
Right. Like the month slides into the day,
从日期滑到事件等等
or the day slides into an event, you know, whatever,
点击之后就滑到了新的 MVC 中
so they slide in as you click on them.
但是代码中会发生什么呢
But what’s happening in your code?
在新的 MVC 滑入之前
Well, there’s an important thing that needs to happen
需要做一件很重要的事情
before a new MVC can slide in,
就是它需要被准备好
which is that it needs to be prepared.
我们回到日历这个例子
So let’s go back to the example of the calendar.
当我点击–
When I click on that –
假设当前日历显示的是月视图
let’s say I’ve got a month’s view showing the calendar
然后我选择了一天
and I pick on a day,
日 MVC 就会滑进来 显示这一天
and now it’s going to slide it in to show me a day.
我需要告诉那个日 MVC 当前选择了哪一天
I need to tell that day MVC what day.
因为那个日 MVC
Okay. Because that day MVC,
也许它可以始终显示当前日期
I guess it could just always show today,
但是日历应用中应该可以显示其他日期
but if you’re a calendar app you want it to be able to show other days,
所以你需要为日 MVC 出现在屏幕上做准备
so you need to prepare that day MVC to come onscreen
告诉它当前选中了哪一天
by telling it what day.
你告诉它之后 它就可以独自运行了
Okay. Once you tell it what day, it’s on its own.
出现在屏幕上 显示选中日期
It just goes off, shows the day,
你可以滚动
you scroll around, you know,
如果在上面点击某处
if you click on a thing,
日 MVC 会将事件详情 MVC 压入显示
it’s the one that pushes again to push in the event detail one,
但是你必须为它进行准备
but you’ve got to prepare it.
MVC 需要提前准备
Okay. So MVCs need to be prepared.
谁来做准备工作呢
Well, who does the preparation?
显然 是你点击的那个 MVC
Obviously, it’s the MVC that you clicked in
是它让其他 MVC 滑进来的
to cause this other MVC to slide in.
在我们刚才做过的例子中
So in the example we just did,
中间有按钮的那个 MVC
the MVC that has the button in it,
它应该有一个方法叫做 prepareForSegue
it should have a method in it, prepareForSegue,
为下一个 MVC 做准备
that prepares the next one over –
为右边的 MVC 出现在屏幕上做准备
the one on the right to come onscreen.
月 MVC 需要有一个 prepareForSegue 方法
The month one has to have a prepareForSegue
为日视图控制器出现在屏幕上做准备
that prepares a day view controller for coming onscreen.
prepareForSegue 的代码是什么样的呢
So what does this prepareForSegue code look like?
首先 它叫做 prepareForSegue: sender:
Okay. First of all, it’s called prepareForSegue colon sender colon,
现在不用考虑参数 sender
don’t worry about that sender argument for now.
用到它的时候 我们再讲
We’ll talk about when that’s useful,
非常少见
it’s a pretty rare case.
通常只需要第一个参数中的信息
Normally, you just need the information that’s in that first argument –
也就是 UIStoryboardSegue
the UIStoryboardSegue.
看到那个 UIStoryboardSegue 了吧
You see that UIStoryboardSegue.
如果你看一下这个类
If you go look at that class,
就会看到两个非常有意思的属性
you’ll see there’s a couple of very interesting properties on it.
一个是标识符
One of it is — one interesting property is identifier.
也就是我们在 Xcode 中输入的字符串 DoSomething
That’s that string we typed in in Xcode — DoSomething.
还记得吗
Remember that?
得到这个 preparedForSegue 时
So when you get this preparedForSegue,
要做的第一件事就是
the first thing you’re going to do is
查看 segue 的标识符
look at the identifier of the segue
获得当前所说的 segue
to see which segue we’re talking about.
我们为什么要这么做呢
Now why do we even need to do that?
答案是 我们可以有多个点触发 segue
The answer is we can have multiple things segue,
我们再回到月视图
so again, let’s go back to the month view.
我可以点击一天 segue 到日视图
I can click on a day and it can segue to a day view,
我也可以点击编辑之类的
but maybe I click on the edit, or something like that,
它就可以 segue 到某个视图上 对月份进行编辑
and it could segue to some view that edits something about the month.
比如每周从周日还是周一开始
Okay. Like, do they start on Sundays or do they start on Mondays,
这种编辑视图
that kind of view.
明白吗 我可以 segue 到不同的视图
See what I mean? So it could segue to a different one,
所以月视图中有两个不同的控件
so you’d have two different controls inside the month view
分别 segue 到不同的 MVC
that are segueing to different MVC
所以我们需要
so we need to know –
通过标识符确认是哪个 segue
we know which one it is by its identifier.
确定目标 segue 之后–
Okay. So, once we’ve checked to see which one we’re talking about here –
我们总会执行这一步
and we always do that,
即便只有一个 segue
even if there’s only one segue,
我们也都会检查标识符
we always check the identifier
确保和 storyboard 中添加的是同一个
just to make sure we’re in sync with what we put in our storyboard,
因为某天我们也许会再添加一个标识符不同的 segue
because some day we may add another segue with a different identifier.
然后 下面一步是
Then, the next thing we do
确定要 segue 到哪个 MVC
is we’re going to say what MVC are we segueing to?
通常情况下 我们知道它的类是什么
Okay. Usually we are going to know what class of thing it is
或者认为我们知道
or think we know,
因为我们知道 segue 的标识符
because we know the identifier of the segue.
如果你在月视图中
So it only makes sense if you’re in the month view
点击了某一天
and you click on that day,
这时候 segue 到日视图控制器才说得通
that thing it’s segueing to better be a day view controller,
如果不是这样的话 你也不知道该做什么 对吧
because you don’t know what else to do if it’s not. Okay.
但是即便这样 我们也会加上
But you still, even so, will usually do
segue.destinationViewController isKindOfClass
segue.destinationViewController isKindOfClass,
后面是我们想要的视图控制器
the view controller we expect.
然后创建一个它的局部变量
Then we’ll make a little local variable with it,
然后取局部变量 doVC 的属性值
and then we’re going to do doVC which is our local variable,
doVC.neededInfo=
dot neededInfo equals,
这算是准备日视图控制器的伪代码
what’s kind of pseudo code for preparing that day view controller.
如果这是日视图的例子
So, if this were the day view example,
这里可能会写成 doVC.date 等于某个 NSDate
probably it would say doVC dot date equals some NSDate.
这样我们就做好了日视图的准备工作
Right? And so now we’ve prepared the day thing.
我们只需要做这些就行了
And that’s all we do here.
其他操作都会神奇地自动执行
Everything else happens by magic.
我们准备好新的 MVC 之后
Once we’ve prepared that new MVC,
它出现在屏幕上 做它要做的事情
it goes onscreen, does what it does.
滑动和动画都不用我们操心
We don’t have to do anything to make things slide or animate,
都是由系统处理的
that’s all handled by the system.
这里系统只需要你做一件事
All the system is asking right here is
就是为 MVC 出现在屏幕上做准备
please prepare this MVC to come onscreen.
这里需要理解一件很重要的事情
Now, very important thing to understand here,
当调用这个方法时
when this is called,
目标 MVC 中的输出口并没有设置好
your outlets are not set in the destination MVC.
这个方法是在 awakeFromNib 和 viewDidLoad 之间被调用的
Okay. So this is between awakeFromNib and viewDidLoad.
非常烦人
This is very annoying. Okay.
我希望不是这样的
I wish this was different.
我相信肯定有这样做的原因
I’m sure there must be a good reason why this is the way it is,
但是这真的很烦人
but it’s very annoying,
因为这种顺序意味着我们传递的所有信息
because it means that any information that you’re passing,
比如传递给日视图的日期
like the day, to the day view,
必须要等到输出口都设置好才能传递
it has to kind of hold on do it until all its outlets are set
然后再在 viewDidLoad 中更新 UI
and then in viewDidLoad, it can go update all its UI.
我这么说明白吗
Does that make sense what I just said?
你需要设置属性
Right. So you’re going to have to have properties
用来保存日期
that are going to have to hold on to the day,
然后在 viewDidLoad 执行时 它才能更新 UI
and then when viewDidLoad happens, then it can update the UI.
我会在示例中进行演示
And I’m going to show you in the demo,
用一种大概算是样板化的方法
kind of a way that we might do it that’s somewhat boiler plate,
或者
or somewhat kind of –
我不知道能不能说它是最好的方法
I don’t know if I want to go so far as to say best practice –
是简单的方法
simple practice for doing that –
用来处理这个方法是在调用 viewDidLoad 之前
for dealing with the fact that this gets called before viewDidLoad,
在输出口没有设好时被调用的问题
okay, before your outlets are set. Okay.
segue 是可以被阻止的
So it is possible to prevent a segue.
对了 这里还有几张幻灯片
I have a few other slides, by the way,
课上我就不讲了
that I’m not going over in lecture,
大家可以下载到
but they’re on what you downloaded,
通读一遍
so you can kind of read through them
查看相关文档 就可以理解了
and look at the documentation to figure it out.
这里我要再讲一些 segue 的内容
But I’m going to talk about a couple of segue things here.
一是你可以阻止 segue 跳转
One is you can prevent a segue from happening
方法是 shouldPerformsegueWithIdentifier: sender:
by doing this shouldPerformsegueWithIdentifier colon sender colon,
方法名就是它的含义
and that’s exactly what it says.
返回 YES 或 NO 来表示是否允许某个 segue 跳转
You return yes or no whether you want that segue to happen.
为什么我们不想允许 segue 跳转呢
Why would you never want — why would you not want this to happen?
比如说你有一个按钮
Let’s say you have a button
通常情况下 点击按钮之后就会进行 segue 跳转
and you click on it and it normally segues,
但是因为某些原因 你不能进行 segue
but for some reason you can’t segue.
也许你没有权限
Okay. Maybe you don’t have permission,
找不到日期了等等
or it can’t find the date, or whatever,
所以这时你希望弹出一个警告
so instead you want to put up an alert
说无法提供信息等等
that says could not, you know, provide the information, or whatever.
不能直接用按钮上的目标操作
You can’t just have a target action from that button
来弹出警告
that puts up the alert.
你需要阻止 segue 跳转的发生
Okay. You need to prevent the segue from happening
并弹出警告
and put up the alert.
所以你需要用这个方法来阻止 segue
So you prevent the segue with this
然后再通过按钮的目标操作
and then you have target action from your button
弹出警告
that puts up the altet.
你显然不想同时弹出警告和进行 segue 跳转
Okay. That obviously, you wouldn’t want to put up the alert and segue,
二者只能执行一项
so it — they want to be mutually exclusive,
这就是阻止 segue 跳转的方法
but this is how you can prevent a segue. Okay.
进入演示之前
Any questions before I dive into a demo
有什么问题吗
to show you all this in action?
好的 我来演示一下
All right. Here we go.
这里我们要做的是
So what we’re going to do here
回到 Attributor
is we are going to go back to Attributor. Right?
不用 Matchismo 了 我们这回用 Attributor 来演示
Instead of Matchismo, we’re going to do this in Attributor.
好了 隐藏其他内容
All right. Let’s hide others here.
Attributor 就是这个样子的
So this is what Attributor looks like,
两天前的例子 希望大家还记得
if you’ll remember, hopefully, from just two days ago.
我们要做的是添加第二个 MVC
And what we’re going to do is we’re going to add a second MVC,
而这个 MVC 要做的是
and what this MVC is going to do is to analyze –
分析某些文本
it’s going to analyze some text
统计彩色字符有多少个
and say how many colored characters in there,
带有轮廓的字符有多少个等等
how many outlined characters in there, etcetera.
所以它会进行统计
Right. So it’s kind of a stat.
告诉你某些文本的统计数据
It’s giving you statistics about some texts.
现在我要把这个 MVC 移到一旁
Now, I’m going to put this aside
单独做这个新的 MVC
and do this new MVC completely independently.
换句话说 我现在甚至不会考虑这个 MVC
In other words, I’m not even going to think about this right now.
我要创建第二个 MVC
I’m going to build the second MVC that does this thing
用来分析文本 得出统计结果
which is analyze text and give you result,
然后我们会用到它
then we’ll use it.
我只是想通过这样做
And I just want to do that to emphasize
强调 MVC 的独立性
how we want MVCs to be independent.
我们来设计那个 MVC
Okay. So let’s design that MVC.
先拖出一个视图控制器
We start by dragging out a view controller,
像这样
just like this.
然后为它新建一个类
Okay. We’re going to create a new class for it.
我要叫它
Okay. And I’m going to call this thing –
它是一个 UIViewController
it’s going to be a UIViewController,
我要叫它
and I’m going to call it –
我们就叫它 TextStatsViewController
let’s call it TextStatsViewController.
我用的应该是这个名字 我看一下 没错
I think that’s the name I used. Make sure I did it. Yeah.
TextStatsViewController
TextStatsViewController.
也可以叫它 AnalyzeTextViewController 等等
We could call it AnalyzeTextViewController, something like that,
但我认为 TextStatsViewController 虽然很难读
but I think TextStatsViewController — although it’s mouthful,
但是具有很好的描述性
is pretty descriptive.
保存在同一目录下
And so we’re going to put it at the same top level there,
我们当然也可以将视图控制器进行分组
and we can of course group our view controllers too.
这是 TextStatsViewController 的代码
Here’s the code for our TextStatsViewController.
这里同样可以看到
You can see again,
自动生成了这个指定初始化方法 我们不需要
we’ve got this nice designated initializer which we don’t want,
还有一些视图控制器生命周期的代码
and we’ve got some view controller lifecycle,
我们也不需要
we don’t want any of that. Okay.
这个 TextStatsViewController
So, this TextStatsViewController,
本质上说 它是可重用的
it is essentially a reusable thing.
需要一个公有 API
It needs a public API.
就像设计卡牌配对游戏时一样
Okay. And just like we did when we designed the card matching game
我们想要先设置一个公有 API
and we kind of tried to come up with a public API first
然后才能考虑如何使用我们的元素
so we could think of how our thing is going to be used,
这里我们要做完全一样的操作
we’re going to do exact same thing here.
转到它的公有接口
So, I’m going to go to the public interface of this.
这是 TextStatsViewController 的公有接口
this is the public interface for TextStatsViewController,
我要增加一个属性
and I’m going to add a property,
nonatomic strong 是一个 NSAttributedString
nonatomic strong, which is a NSAttributedString,
叫做 textToAnalyze 待分析文本
which is the textToAnalyze.
这个 MVC 的工作方式就是
Okay. So the way this MVC is going to work
你为它设置一个 textToAnalyze
is you set it a textToAnalyze
是一个属性化字符串
which is an attributed string,
然后它会对其进行分析
and it’s going to analyze it.
就是这样 它就是这个功能
Okay. That’s it. That’s what it does.
这就是它存在的意义
Okay. That’s its entire reason for being. Okay.
但它是一个完整的 MVC
But it’s an entire MVC,
所以要有相应 UI 等
so it’s going to have the UI to do that,
来实现这个功能
all that stuff to do that.
那么如何实现呢
So, how are we going to implement something like this?
我要先思考一下
Well, I’m going to start by thinking about
如果我是这个 MVC
how I want to react if I’m this MVC
有人设置了 textToAnalyze 我要如何反应
when people set my textToAnalyze.
显然 如果有人设置了 textToAnalyze
And obviously, if someone sets my textToAnalyze,
使用 setTextToAnalyze 这个公有方法
using setTextToAnalyze, right, the public method.
显然 我需要在这里设置变量
Obviously, I want to set my variable here,
我还要更新我的 UI
but I’m also going to update my UI.
只要有人设置了要分析的文本
Okay. So anytime someone sets the text to analyze,
我就要更新 UI
I’m going to update my UI.
所以 我并不希望我的 UI
So, I don’t want to allow my UI to ever get out of sync
和我的模型不同步
with what is essentially my model.
从本质上说 它就是这个 MVC 的模型
Okay. This is essentially the model for this MVC,
就是要分析的文本
is the text to analyze.
当然 我们还要加上 updateUI
So, of course, we’re going to want nice updateUI,
和另一个 MVC 中的很类似
very similar to that we had in the other one,
我们一会实现它
and we’ll do that in a minute. Okay.
还有一个时间点可能需要更新 UI
But, there’s another time here when I might want to update my UI,
就是在 viewWillAppear 视图将要出现时
and that is in viewWillAppear.
这又回到了我们以前讲过的内容
And that’s back to what we were talking about before,
如果我不在屏幕上的时候 textToAnalyze 被设置了怎么办
which is that if this textToAnalyze gets set when I’m not onscreen,
也许是在输出口没有设置好的时候
maybe before my outlets are set,
我希望视图将要出现时同步数据
okay, I want to come along when view will appear
确保 UI 同步
and make sure my UI is in sync.
因为显然 这个 updateUI 要向我的视图发送消息
Okay. Because this updateUI is obviously going to be taking to my view
如果输出口没有设好 它不会做任何操作的
and if my outlets aren’t set, it won’t do anything. Okay.
这个方法显然马上会在 prepareForSegue 中被调用
So this is obviously gonna get called in prepareForSegue in a moment,
所以我要这样做
so that’s why I’m doing this,
一般来说 在这两个地方都更新 UI
but this is also kind of a generically good thing to update UI there,
是比较好的做法
and update it here.
有人可能会认为 真浪费
Now you might argue oh, what a waste.
如果调用它的时候 输出口设好了呢
What if this is called and your outlets are set?
你在这里更新了 UI 然后出现时又更新了一遍
You updated UI and then you appeared and you updated UI again.
所以有人可能会认为这样做比较好
So, one might argue that it’s a good thing to do this.
self.view.window 是当前视图所在窗口
Okay. Self dot view dot window is the window that your view is in,
view 指的是你的 MVC 的顶级视图
view is the top level view of your MVC,
如果它是 nil 那么你现在不在屏幕上
and if that’s nil, then you’re not onscreen right now.
所以这样写的意思是
So what this says is,
如果有人设置了待分析的文本 而且我在屏幕上
if someone sets the text I’m supposed to analyze and I’m onscreen,
那么我最好更新我的 UI
then I’d better update my UI.
否则就让 viewWillAppear 替我执行
Otherwise, I’ll let viewWillAppear do it for me,
因为我现在不在屏幕上 但最终会出现在屏幕上
because I’m not onscreen and I’m eventually going to come onscreen.
实际上 除非我出现在屏幕上 否则我不会分析文本的
In fact, I’ll never analyze my text unless I get put onscreen,
这样的性能也很好
so it’s kind of good performance too,
尽管分析文本会变得不太重要
although analyzing text is going to be trivial. Okay.
这是一种常用的模式
So this is kind of a common pattern
设置输出口
to have outlets that you set
如果你在屏幕上的话就更新
that if you’re onscreen will update,
否则就等着让 viewWillAppear 来做
otherwise, you wait and let viewWillAppear do it.
明白吧 好的
Okay. All right.
我们讲讲如何更新 UI
So let’s talk about update UI and how that’s going to work.
先创建视图
Well, let’s build our view
方便大家知道我们要创建的 UI 是怎样的
so you know what our UI is that we want to build here.
UI 会非常非常简单
So, I’m going to make this really, really simple,
只是添加两个标签
so I’m just going to have a couple of labels here.
这里写上 0 个彩色字符
I’m going to say zero colorful characters.
我们会用在 Matchismo 中用过的
Okay. And then we’re going to do the same thing we did
处理分数的方法
with the score in Matchismo
用打印函数来修改标签
to change that with the printf thing,
再添加一条带有轮廓字符的统计信息
and then we’ll also keep track of outlined characters,
这个文本分析器中
but you could imagine that this text analyzer
应该还有很多其他数据
would have a whole bunch of other lines,
分析随机属性化文本的其他数据
where it’d analyze other thing that was in random attributed text.
字体 加粗 斜体等等
Okay. Font, bold, italic, etcetera,
但是这里我们就简化一下
but again, we’re going to make this simple.
我需要更新这两条数据
So I need to update these two things with –
通过分析模型 这里的这个模型
by analyzing whatever my model, this model right here,
分析它的属性化字符串的内容情况
contains in terms of attributed strings.
我要怎么实现呢
So how am I going to do that?
我要为大家展示
Well, I’m going to do that in a way that shows off a little bit
如何分析属性化字符串
how we analyze attributed strings.
我会快速输入代码
Okay. I’m going to type this code in pretty quick
因为显然我们时间不够了
because we’re time constrained, obviously,
但大家要确保自己理解了这段代码
but you should make sure you understand this code.
非常简单和直接
It’s very simple and straightforward,
但是真的需要你理解属性化字符串
but it really requires that you understand attributed strings,
所以这也同时检查了
so it’s a little bit of a double check
大家对于属性化字符串的理解
of your attributed string understanding.
我要做的是
So what I’m going to do is
添加一个方法 叫做 charactersMatching–
I’m going to have a method called charactersMatching –
不如我们用这个吧
or we’ll just use this one like
charactersWithAttribute: (NSString )attributeName
charactersWithAttribute NSString attributeName. Okay.
这个方法要做的是
So what this is going to do is
对 textToAnalyze 进行查找
it’s going to look in my textToAnalyze
看有哪些字符具有这个属性
for any characters that have this attribute,
比如 NSForegroundColor 和 strokeWidth 等
like NSForegroundColor attribute or in strokeWidth, or something like that,
这个方法会返回一个字符串
and it’s going to return a string
复制了所有符合条件的字符
that has all those characters cloned onto it.
然后在 UI 中
And then in my UI,
我只要知道长度就可以得到字符的数量
I’ll just specify how many of them there are by checking the length,
通过字符串的长度
okay, of that string.
有人可能会问 为什么要这么麻烦地收集字符
And you might ask why am I going to all the troubles to collect them up,
等下就知道了
and you’ll see that later.
如何把字符收集起来呢
Okay. So, how would I collect this up?
我这样做是想为大家演示它是如何作用的
I’m doing it mostly because I want to show you how that would work.
我要创建一个可变属性化字符串 用来收集字符
So I’m gonna create a mutable attributed string to collect all this into.
叫它 characters
I’ll call it characters,
把两边的面板隐藏 腾出更大空间
and let’s make more space here on both sides.
好的
Okay.
然后是 [NSMutableAttributedString alloc] init
So I’m just going to say NSMutableAttributedString alloc init,
现在这是一个空的可变字符串
so here’s an empty mutable string
我要在其中添加字符 然后返回字符串
that I’m going to put the characters in and return. Okay.
所以在中间我需要收集符合条件的字符
So, in here I need to collect all this stuff.
我要做什么呢
So what am I going to do?
实际上 我要做的是
I’m actually just going to
创建一个 while 循环 依次检查字符
do a while loop that goes through and looks at every character.
再简单不过了
Okay. Couldn’t be simpler.
这里写 int index=0
So I’ll say int index equals zero
当 index 小于 self.textToAnalyze 的长度时
while this index is less than the self textToAnalyze length,
while (index<[self.textToAnalyze lenth])
oops, length.
我就会收集字符
Then I’m going to collect the characters. Okay.
这里多了一个方括号
Too many square brackets there. Okay.
到这里大家都明白吧
So everyone understands this part so far, right?
这部分最简单了
This part couldn’t be simpler.
我们继续
So, now let’s go ahead
获取这个属性的值
and get the value of this attribute
这个位置的字符的属性值
at this character.
叫做 value 它在这里是一个 ID 类型
So that’s value, and the value’s an ID here,
因为它有可能是一种颜色 一种字体 对吧
because it could be a color, it could be a font. Right?
可能是一个 NSNumber
It could be NSNumber, so I’m –
这样 ID 类型就派上用场了
this is where ID comes in handy dandy.
然后是 self.textToAnalyze attribute:attributeName
So let’s say self dot textToAnalyze attribute colon attributeName
atIndex: index effectiveRange
atIndex: index effectiveRange. Okay.
还记得这个 effectiveRange 吧
So this effectiveRange, remember I told you,
它会返回具有相同属性的字符范围
is gonna return the range that this attribute is the same for.
如果连续 12 个字符都具有这个属性
Right. So if this attribute is there for 12 characters in a row,
它就会返回连续 12 个这样的范围
it’s going to return this range 12 in a row,
我要得到这个范围
so I’m going to capture that range,
你们会看到我为什么要这样做
and you’ll see why I want that.
我最好新建一个局部变量
Okay. So I better create a local variable
NSRange range
NSRanger, no, NSRange. Oh, hello, range, range.
这只是这个结构体的局部变量 range
So this is just a local variable range for this struct
我要传递一个指针给它
and I’m just going to pass a pointer to it,
effectiveRange 把结构体填满
so that it fills that struct out with the effectiveRange.
有问题吗
Got any questions there?
好的
All right.
如果 value 不为空
So, if the value is set,
那就是我想要的
okay, that’s what I’m looking for.
我要找那些设置了这个属性的字符
I’m looking for characters where this attribute is set.
如果我查看的属性是前景色
Okay. So, if I’m looking at foreground color,
那这就是带颜色的字符
this would be colored characters.
如果我查看的是描边宽度
If I’m looking at stroke width,
那就是带有轮廓的字符
it would be outlined characters.
所以如果 value 不为空
So if the value is set,
我就要将它加到 characters 中
then I’m going to take the characters and append onto it
textToAnalyze attributedSubstringFromRange
the textToAnalyze attributedSubstringFromRange,
然后是我得到的范围 range
that range I just got back.
大家都明白吗
Everyone make sense there?
这里我收集了符合属性条件的字符
So I just collected those characters that matched that attribute,
我还想加上
and I also want to say –
这里可以用 index++ 进入下一个 index
I could say index plus plus and just go to the next index,
但是实际上 我们知道字符范围
but actually know that this range of character
结束的位置是 range.location+range.length
ends at range dot location plus range dot length.
所以不需要逐一检查
Right. So there’s no need to check –
我已经得到了这个范围
I already grabbed this range,
只要直接跳到这个范围的末尾就可以了
so I need now to jump to the end of this range.
如果这个字符没有设置这个属性
If the attribute is not set on this character,
那我确实需要移到下一个 index
then I do need to move to the next thing.
移到下一个字符
Okay. To the next character,
因为我是在这个 while 循环中
because I’m in this while loop right here,
需要循环执行
I need to go round and round.
好的 就是这样
Okay. So that’s it.
希望大家都理解了这段代码
Hopefully, you all understand this code.
如果没有 下面再看看
If you don’t, you definitely want to offline,
确保自己理解了这部分的工作原理
make sure you understand how this works
理解了可变字符串
so that you understand mutable strings
理解了属性化字符串
or attributed strings. Okay.
注意这里返回的是一个不可变属性化字符串
So now, notice that I’m returning a non-mutable attributed string here
而它显然是一个可变属性化字符串
and this is clearly a mutable attributed string,
这样完全没问题
and that’s perfectly fine.
这样意味着 不管是谁调用这个方法
What that says is whoever’s calling this,
都不应该认为它是可变的
shouldn’t rely on this being mutable.
应该假设它是不可变的
They should assume it’s not mutable.
updateUI 会调用这个方法
And so, updateUI is going to call this
它不应该尝试改变这些字符
and it should be sure not to try and change these characters,
如果不进行类型转换 这也是不允许的
and it won’t be allowed to either without doing some sort of casting
因为编译器不允许赋值给可变字符串
because the compiler is not gonna let you assign this to a mutable string.
我把这个方法移到上面这里
I’m going to move this up here like this,
我们继续 用下面这行代码
and so let’s go ahead and use this.
可能看起来很长
This might seem like a really long line of code,
但也很简单
but it’s pretty straightforward,
我们需要添加一些指向它们的输出口
so we need to have some outlets that point to these things.
指向这两个标签 我们做一下
Right. These little guys right here, so let’s do that.
这正好是我刚才说过的内容的例子
Okay. So, here’s an example of exactly what I was talking about.
我想在这里创建一个输出口
I want to create an outlet here
怎么回事
and what’s going on?
为什么不能创建这个输出口呢
How come I can’t create this outlet?
是自动没错
Okay. This is on automatic.
怎么回事呢
What’s going on here?
答案是 它还是一个 UIViewController
Well the answer is, this is still UIViewController,
所以我需要转到这里
so I need to go over here,
打开标识符检查器
go to here,
这里现在是 UIViewController
and instead of having UIViewController here,
我要改成 TextStatsViewController
I need TextStatsViewController.
看看发生了什么
Okay. Now look what happened.
系统自动更新了代码
It automatically updated this.
自动模式发挥了它的作用
Okay. The automatic did its automatic job.
现在我就可以在这里按住 control 键拖动到这里了
Okay. So now I can control drag from here to here –
我们叫它 colorfulCharactersLabel 彩色字符标签
we’ll call this colorfulCharactersLabel,
我还要从这里拖动到这里
and I’ll also drag from here to here
我要叫它 outlinedCharactersLabel 带有轮廓字符标签
and we’ll call this outlinedCharactersLabel. Okay.
看懂了吗
Everyone see that?
剩下要做的
All right. So all we have left to do here
就是实现 updateUI 方法
is implement our updateUI
让这两个标签
to make these two labels here
能够正确显示字符串长度
properly display the length of the characters
而长度是通过下面的 charactersWithAttribute 计算出的
that we calculated with this charactersWithAttribute down here.
腾出更大空间
So let’s make a lot more space.
转到这里 只显示视图控制器
Let’s go over here, just showing our view controller.
实际上 updateUI 方法中要做的是
And in updateUI all we really need to do
得到具有指定属性的字符
is get the characters with the given attribute,
无论属性是颜色还是轮廓
whether it be color or the outline
然后计算字符个数
and count how many characters in there.
我们用 self–
So let’s do self dot –
先用 self.charactersWithAttribute
sorry, let’s do self dot charactersWithAttribute first.
我们先看颜色属性的情况
And let’s do the color ones first,
对应属性是 NSForegroundColorAttributeName
which the attribute there would be the ForegroundColorAttributeName.
现在我们得到了这些字符
So now we’ve got these characters.
看一下
And let’s see.
得到字符后 就可以计算字符个数了
Now that we have them, we can count them.
方法是发送字符串的长度
So let’s do that by sending length of the string.
现在我们就知道这里有多少个字符了
So now we know how many characters there are here.
现在我们就可以更新那个字段了
So now we can update that field,
也就是 self.colorfulCharactersLabel.text
which is our self dot colorfulCharactersLabel text.
然后是 NSString stringWithFormat:
And we’ll do that by saying NSString stringWithFormat,
@”%d colorful characters”
percent D colorful characters,
参数就是刚才写好的这个计算结果
and the argument is this thing we just calculated right here.
这个写好了
Okay? So we got that.
再做一次
And let’s do the exact same thing here
带有轮廓字符的情况
with the outlined characters.
这里改成 outlined characters
And these are outlined characters.
这里改成 NSStrokeWidthAttributeName
And this is the NSStrokeWidthAttributeName.
我们找到了具有该属性的字符
Okay? So we’ve went and found the characters that have that attribute,
计算了它们的数量
found out how many there are,
然后创建了一个格式化字符串
and then we created a string with format
显示在标签上
that displayed that into the label.
这样并不是完全正确的
Okay. This is not 100% correct,
如果设置的颜色是黑色呢
because what if the color set on something is black?
并不是彩色的字符
It’s not a very colorful character.
或者如果设置了描边宽度
Or what if the stroke width is set,
但是宽度设为 0 呢
but it’s set to zero,
所以这并不是一个很好的实现方法 但是很简单
so this is not a great implementation, but it’s simple.
能够给你一种思路
It gives you the idea.
有时 我喜欢在新建 MVC 时测试一下
Now one thing I like to do when I build a new MVC sometimes is test it.
测试的方法是添加一个简单的 viewDidLoad 方法
Okay. So I’m going to test this by adding a little viewDidLoad.
这是 viewDidLoad
Okay. So here’s viewDidLoad,
这里要写的是 self.textToAnalyze=
and what I’m going to do is self dot textToAnalyze equals
[NSAttributedString alloc] initWithString:@”test” attributes:
NSAttributedString alloc initWithString test attributes,
后面我要加上某些测试属性
and I’m going to put some test attributes in here
比如前景色为绿色
like NSForegroundColor, green,
再加上描边宽度属性
and also let’s put NSStrokeWidth –
比如 -3 之类的
call it minus three, or something like that.
好了 我写好了
Right. So I have this.
现在 当这个 MVC 出现时
So now, when this MVC appears,
它的 viewDidLoad 方法会设置它的模型
its viewDidLoad is going to set its own model,
是一种很好的测试方法
which is kind of a good testing thing,
我们回去做一下
so let’s go back and do that.
我们如何做这个测试呢
And how would we do that test?
这里是我们的 storyboard
So we got our storyboard here,
我们直接把这个箭头移到这里
what if we just pick this guy up and put it over here?
现在我再运行这个应用
Now when I run this app,
就会直接来到这个 MVC 跳过左边这个
it’s going to go straight to this MVC and just bypass –
不会用到左边这个
this is not even going to be used right now,
因为我只是测试右边这个 MVC
because I’m just going to test this guy.
我们试试
So let’s try that.
看看我有没有忘记什么
See if I forgot anything.
不是模拟器 我换一下
Oops, simulator. I’ll do this on the –
我们在设备上运行
Let’s go put it on the device.
test 这个词中有四个字符
Okay. So the word test has four characters in it,
希望运行出来显示的是
so hopefully this is going to come up and say
4 个彩色字符 4 个带有轮廓字符
four colorful characters and four outline characters,
是运行正常的
so it’s working.
我可以删掉一个属性
And I could go delete one of those attributes,
检查数量是否显示为 0
make sure it says zero.
还可以换一个比 test 长的单词
I could change the word to be longer than test
检查显示数量是否大于 4
to make sure it says more than four.
明白吗
You see what I mean?
明白我是如何测试这个 MVC 检查它是否正常运行的吗
See how I can kind of test this MVC to make sure it’s working?
但我们现在就相信它
So, we’re going to take our word for it though
这样测试就够了 它运行正常
that’s enough testing and that it’s working,
删掉 viewDidLoad
so I’m going to get rid of viewDidLoad.
这些也可以放到
This is something you might put this in
ifdef 之类的测试中
some sort of ifdef testing or something like that.
大家都知道怎么做
You know how to do all that,
也可以那样做
so you could do that as well,
我就直接删掉 viewDidLoad 了
but I’m just going to delete viewDidLoad,
现在这里我有了一个非常好用的 MVC
but I have a really nice working MVC right here
能告诉我某段给定文本中
that tells how many characters are colored and outlined
有多少彩色和带有轮廓的字符
in a given piece of text.
显然 现在应用可以从这里开始了
Well now, obviously, I could use if from this guy –
我们把箭头移回去
let’s move this guy back.
我要把它们放到一个导航控制器中
And I’m going to put these inside of a navigation controller,
我还要在导航控制器顶栏上
and I’m going to actually add a button
添加一个按钮
to the navigation controller’s bar,
在这个 MVC 显示时出现
when this one’s visible,
用来 segue 到这个 MVC
that will segue over to this guy.
我们做一下
Okay. So let’s do that.
先把它加到导航控制器中
Let’s put it in navigation controller first.
腾出更大空间
More space here.
我只要选择嵌入导航控制器
so I’m just going to embed in navigation controller. Right.
放进去了 上面自动添加了一栏
Boom, puts it in. Okay. It got a bar.
注意这个 MVC 并没有顶栏
Notice that this one did not get a bar.
为什么 因为还没有元素能够 segue 到它这里
Why? Because there’s nothing that segues to this yet,
导航控制器中没有
that’s inside this navigation controller.
还发生了一件不太好的事
Another bad thing happened though.
CS193p Rocks 不见了
I lost my CS193P rocks.
我们知道 CS193p 确实很棒
Okay. And we know that CS193P does rock,
所以我们不希望这句话被遮掉
so we do not want it blocked like that,
如果某个元素像这样被遮掉了
so one thing you can do is if something gets blocked like this,
你想着 我得把它改好
you know like, oh no, I’ve got to go fix that,
你可以直接删除导航控制器
you can just delete the navigation controller
就会回到之前的状态
and you’ll be back where you were,
或者点击撤消
or you can hit undo.
实际上 我要删掉它
So I’m actually going to get rid of this
将它放到灰栏上
and put it in that gray bar instead.
放在那里很合适
It’s a perfectly reasonable place for it to go.
也许我应该把上边界降低一点
Maybe I’ll move this down a little bit
确保等下大小合适
to make sure it fits on there.
现在再选中它
So now let’s go back and select this again
选择嵌入
and embed it.
现在又回到了导航控制器中
Okay. So now we’re back in here.
现在我可以把 CS193p Rocks 放在这里
All right. And now I can put my CS193p rocks here.
放在这里很合适
Okay. Perfectly reasonable place to put it.
得到了这个界面
And I’ve got this.
还可以往上拉一点
Maybe I would line that up there or there,
根据蓝线的指引
depends on where the blue lines say. Okay.
得到了这个界面
So I got that.
现在我想在这里添加一个小按钮
Now I want to put a little button right here,
都还记得怎么做吧
so if everyone remembers how to do that.
滚动到下面
We go all the way down to the bottom here
找到 Bar Button Item 栏按钮项 在这里
and we find bar button item, which is right here,
将它拖出
and we drag it up.
放在这里
We put it right there.
它是用来显示统计数据的
This is going to show the stats,
我就叫它 Stats
so I’m going to call this Stats.
好的
All right.
每次点击 Stats 时
And now, every time I click on stats,
我想让这个 MVC 滑进来 替换掉左边的 MVC
I want this MVC to slide in here and replace this one,
在 Stats 上按住 control 键拖动到这里
so I’m going to control drag to here.
导航控制器中的 segue 类型都是 push
Okay. Inside of navigation controller it’s always push.
这里出现了一个 segue
Okay. There’s a segue right here.
如果我们点击这个 segue 转到属性检查器
If we click on this segue and go to the attributes inspector
可以看到它是一个 push 类型 segue
and see that it’s a push segue,
我们要叫它 Show Stats 显示统计数据
and we’re going to call this show stats
或者换个更好的 Analyze Text 分析文本
or even maybe better, Analyze Text.
标识符最好选择一个
Okay. So, we want to have something in there
能够清楚说明 segue 作用的名称
that makes it clear what this segue does.
在这里 它的作用是分析文本
It analyzes the text in this case.
我们要做的最后一件事是
Okay. Now the last thing we need to do
为这个 MVC 出现在屏幕上做准备
is prepare this MVC to come onscreen,
也就是将模型设置为这个文本视图中的文本
basically, by setting its model to be the text that’s in this text view.
要在这里实现
Right. So we do that in here.
让右边 MVC 出现在屏幕上的准备工作是由它完成的
The preparation for this to come onscreen is done by this guy,
因为 segue 是由它发出的
because this guy’s the guy causing the segue.
我们转到这里
So let’s go here.
我们是在自动模式下
As we do this we’re on automatic,
所以我们可以看到它的代码 在这里
so we’re going to see this guy’s code. Here it is.
希望大家还记得上次的代码
Okay. Hopefully, you remember this code from last time,
我们来添加 prepareForSegue 方法
and let’s go ahead and put the prepareForSegue.
放在上面 这样我更顺手
We’ll put it at the top because it works nicer for me.
prepareForSegue
prepareForSegue.
在这个 prepareForSegue 方法中
All right. And all we have to do inside this prepareForSegue
我们只要为这个 segue 做准备
is prepare for this particular segue.
我们只有这一个 segue
It’s the only segue we have,
把代码区拉大一点
so I’m going to make more space here,
往这边滚动一下 这样在我们编写代码的时候
actually let’s scroll over so you can see the segue in your mind,
大家能看到这个 segue
while we’re working on this.
再选中它 好了
Just click this back again. There we go.
那么在 prepareForSegue 中我们做什么呢
Okay. So in prepareForSegue what do we do?
就像我刚才说过的 我们要做的第一件事
Well, like I said, the first thing we’re going to do
就是确保目标 segue 就是这个特定的 segue
is we’re going to make sure we’re talking about this particular segue,
也就是 Analyze Text
which is the Analyze Text one.
当然 如果你在这里输错了
Now, of course, if you mistype this here,
不会得到任何警告之类的
you’re not going to get any warning or anything like that,
如果这里输错了 它只是不会正常运行
or if you mistype it over there, and it’s just not going to work,
因为不能正确准备那个 MVC
because it’s not going to prepare that MVC properly,
我觉得系统功能在这里有点缺陷
so it’s a little bit of a weakness I think of the way this system works,
只要增加一个调试操作
but it’s just a debugging thing
就能检查这里的文本是否与 segue 标识符一致
to make sure your text here matches the text there.
我知道 当我在这里进行 segue 跳转时
All right. So I know that when I’m segueing here,
需要用到这个 TextStatsViewController
I need to use this TextStatsViewController.
我可以在这里导入目标 MVC 的类
Okay. So it’s okay for me to import that MVC’s class in here,
因为它基本算是我的视图的一部分
because it’s part of my view almost,
所以你可以认为
so you can kind of think of it –
统计 MVC 是另一个 MVC 视图的一部分
the stats as being part of the view of this other one,
是下一级
because it’s sub — you know, a sub thing,
所以可以这样做
so it’s okay to do that,
但是我最好再确认一下我们要 segue 去的
but I better make sure that the destination view controller
目标视图控制器属于 TextStatsViewController 类
that we’re gonna be segueing to is kind of TextStatsViewController.
如果是的话 我就在这里创建一个局部变量
Okay. But if it is, then I’ll create a little local variable here,
tsvc=(TextStatsViewController *)
text stats view controller equals TextStatsViewController.
这个操作
This is actually not necessary,
并不是强制要求
this one I’m doing right here,
但是我个人喜欢这样做
but I personally like to do it,
因为我喜欢创建一个局部变量
just because I like to have, you know, a local variable
这样能够直接用 tsvc.textToAnalyze=
that I can do things like tsvc dot textToAnalyze equals.
现在我是在为它做准备
Okay. So here I’m preparing it.
它需要什么呢
Okay. What does it need?
需要我的正文文本
It needs my body text.
还记得上次讲过的内容吗
Okay. Remember from last time?
这个文本视图是 self.body
This text view right here is self dot body,
textStorage 是一个 NSMutableAttributedString
and the textStorage is the NSMutableAttributedString.
这是一个 NSAttributedString
This is an NSAttributedString,
但是可以这样赋值
but it’s okay to assign that,
因为可变字符串也属于属性化字符串
because a mutable string is a regular attributed string,
所以这样是完全没问题的
so this is perfectly legal,
就是这样了
and so that’s it.
我们需要做的就是这些
That’s all that’s necessary for us to do.
现在再运行一下
And now if we run,
大家会看到
you will see
首先 我们出现在一个导航控制器中
that first of all, we come up inside of a navigation controller.
之前的页面还在这里
Okay. We still have our thing here.
依旧可以选择文本
We can still select text.
如果打开统计页面 显示的是 0 个彩色字符
If we bring up the stats, there’s zero colorful characters.
我还没有设置颜色
I didn’t color anything.
点击返回之后 系统释放了那个文本分析 MVC
When I hit back, it just dealloc that text analyze.
我们重新设置一下
Let’s go ahead and make a new one here.
变为橙色 加上轮廓 加点紫色
Orange and maybe some outline, and maybe some purple,
再看统计结果 14 个彩色字符 7 个带有轮廓字符
and now stats — 14 colorful, seven outlined,
非常好用
okay, working like a charm.
我们也许可以为一串字符添加轮廓
Maybe we’ll make a whole bunch of outlined here.
再看统计结果 250 个
Okay. Stats — 250.
就是这样
Okay. So that’s it.
都明白了吗
Everyone got that?
你们要在作业中完成这部分
So you will be doing this on your homework.
实际上 你们需要将它们
In fact, you’ll be taking this
放入一个选项卡栏控制器中
and putting it inside of a tab bar controller,
所以你们要实现两项内容
so you’ll be doing double duty.
剩下五分钟
So let’s talk about tab bar controller
我们来讲一下选项卡栏控制器
in the last five minutes that we have here.
在此之前还有什么问题吗
Any questions about that before I go on to tab bar controller?
看了演示就能明白了吧
It all makes sense once you see it. Right?
有许多组成部分 但是能够组合在一起
There’s a number of components to it, but they kind of fit together.
好的 接着讲选项卡栏控制器
All right. Tab bar controller.
这是我最喜欢的选项卡栏控制器应用示例
Here is my favorite tab bar controller application example,
iOS7 的时钟应用
which is the clock app on iOS seven.
可以看到底部有一个选项卡栏 上面有四个选项卡
You can see it has a tab bar across the bottom there and four tabs.
相互之间完全独立
Each of these four tabs is completely independent of the other
选项卡栏中的 MVC 就应该是这样
and that’s the way MVCs inside a tab bar controller should be,
相互完全独立
completely independent of each other.
如果 MVC 间是相关的 你也许就需要用导航控制器了
If they’re dependent, you probably want a navigation controller.
或者如果是在 iPad 上
Okay. Or if they’re in an iPad,
也许可以用弹出窗口之类的
you might want to a popover, or something like that,
但是 iPhone 应用中需要的是导航控制器
but on an iPhone you probably want a navigation controller
如果 MVC 间有依赖关系的话
if you have a dependency.
选项卡栏控制器是怎样工作的呢
All right. So how does tab bar controller work?
它是非常简单的控制器
Very, very simply controller,
有一个属性叫做 viewControllers
it has a property called viewControllers,
是一个 MVC 的数组 UIViewController 的数组
which is an array of MVCs — UIViewControllers,
MVC 的控制器组成的数组
basically, the controllers of the MVCs.
数组中有多少个控制器
And how ever many you have,
底部就有多少个小选项卡
that’s how many little tabs you’ll have on the bottom.
而在 storyboard 中创建连接的方法
Okay. And this — to create these connections in your storyboard –
同样是按住 control 键进行拖拽
surprise, control drag.
你只要拖出一个 UITabBarController
Okay. So you just drag a UITabBarController out
然后按住 control 键拖动到
and then just control drag to all the controllers
各选项卡对应的控制器上
that you want to be the various tabs.
Timer 和小图标是如何出现在上面的呢
Now, how does the word timer and the little icon there appear.
Timer 是 UIViewController 的标题
Well, the timer is going to be the UIViewController’s title,
和分屏视图控制器顶部显示的一样
the same thing that will appear in the top of a split view controller,
而图标呢
and the icon,
UIViewController 有一个属性叫做 tabBarItem
there’s actually a UIViewController property called tabBarItem,
里面有图标
and inside there is the icon
还有其他元素 比如小气泡
and a few other things like the badge,
就是一个小圆圈 里面有数字或字母
which is a little round circle with a number or a letter in it,
可以显示在上面
which you can put on there.
这就是设置这些元素的方法
So that’s how these things get set,
但是在这里我就不演示了
but I’m not even showing you that here,
因为通常是在 storyboard 中进行设置
because usually you set them in the storyboard.
在 storyboard 中设置图标和文字
Okay. You set this icon and this text in the storyboard.
最好在那里设置
That’s the best place to set these things.
如果你有四个以上控制器呢
Now, what if you have more than four controllers
五个以上呢
or more than five, actually?
会发生什么
Then what happens?
会出现一个 More 更多的选项卡
Then a little more tab is going to appear.
在右下角 看到了吗
See it down there in the corner,
点击它之后
and when you click that
会出现一个界面显示全部控制器
there’s going to be this UI that’s presented that allows you to –
用户可以从中选择四个显示在底部
the user to pick which four they want down there.
可以来回交换
Swap them back and forth,
挺好用的
okay, which is kind of cool.
这都是自动完成的
And that happens automatically.
将更多按钮放在那里 系统会自动执行
You put that more button on there, it just does it.
替你完成相关操作
It does it for you.
非常好用
So that’s really cool.
我其实不推荐 UI 上的选项卡多于五个
Okay. So I actually don’t recommend UIs that have more than five tabs.
我认为这样对用户来说很麻烦
I think this is a little cumbersome for users,
但有些地方需要这样做
but there are some places it would make sense.
这个应用就还不错 比较合理
In this app, it’s not bad. It kind of makes sense.
这是 iPod 应用之类的 音乐应用
This is the iPod app, or whatever, your music app.
所以这样做是有道理的
So it kind of makes some sense here.
不管怎样 如果你确实需要五个以上 那就是这样用的
But anyway, if you do need to do that, that’s how it works.
最后几分钟
So let’s, in the last couple of minutes here,
我们看看在 Xcode 中如何创建选项卡栏控制器
look in Xcode and see what it looks like to make a tab bar controller.
和几张幻灯片之前展示的一样
So this is the same thing I was just showing a few slides earlier.
可以看到导航控制器中那个中间有按钮的 MVC
You see the navigation controller with the MVC that has the button
然后从它 segue 到下一个 MVC
and then it just — you know, it segues to the next one,
我要把它放在一个选项卡栏控制器中
so I’m actually going to put this in a tab bar controller,
所以它会是一个选项卡
so it’s going to be one of the tabs,
然后让另一个空白视图作为另一个选项卡
and then I’m just going to have like a blank view be the other one.
看见右下的选项卡栏控制器了吗
Okay. So, see the tab bar controller there?
将它拖出
I’m dragging it out.
拖出它时
When you drag it out,
它会自带两个空白场景
it’s going to come along with two blank ones, okay,
两个空白无物的
two empty blank ones,
大部分情况下 你并不需要
which very much of the time you don’t want.
这里我会留下一个 删掉另一个
In this case, I’m going to keep one of them, get rid of the other one,
只是为了给大家示范如何实现
just to show you how that’s done.
当你放下它时 可能会遮挡其他 MVC
So when you drop it, it might overlap other ones.
当然 在 storyboard 中
Obviously, in the storyboard,
为了显示效果 你可以随意移动 MVC
you can drag these MVCs anyway you want to make them look nice.
如果它们之间有 segue 等连线
If they happen to be connected by a segue or something,
在移动时 系统会自动重绘连接线
it’ll automatically redraw that line for you as you move it.
这是很好的
It’s really quite nice in that way.
可以想象 storyboard 可以变得非常庞大
You can imagine that these storyboards get very large.
比如有 100 个 storyboard 怎么操作呢
With 100 storyboards in there how does it even work.
如果你看右下角
Well, if you look down in the lower right corner there,
可以看到一个放大镜
you’ll see there’s a magnifying glass,
可以用它放大或缩小
you can zoom in and out.
可以大幅度缩小
Okay. Zoom way out.
如果你有 100 个 MVC 可以缩小到一屏上
If you have 100, you can see all 100 at the same time.
放大到显示某个视图控制器
Zoom in all the way to zooming in all the way in on one view controller
然后你就可以编辑那个视图控制器
and then you can edit that view controller.
只有将某个视图控制器放大
You can’t edit a view controller itself
你才能对它进行编辑
unless you’ve zoomed in all the way. Okay.
现在我有两个空白场景
So here I’ve got two blank ones.
我并不是都想要
I don’t want them both,
所以我只要选中其中一个
so I’m just going to select one of them,
变为蓝色
make it blue,
和之前讲过的一样
as we talked about before,
点击删除 它就消失了
and hit delete, and it’s gone.
剩下另外一个
So I’ve still got the other one. Okay.
现在我要用 control 拖拽
And now I’m gonna hook that navigation controller in there
将导航控制器连接起来
by control dragging.
按住 control 键从选项卡栏控制器
So I’m control dragging from the tab bar controller
拖动到导航控制器
to the navigation controller,
进行 control 拖拽时
and when you do this control drag,
会弹出这个 segue 列表
it’s going to put up this little segue thing,
如果是一个选项卡栏控制器
but when it’s a tab bar controller,
那这里就只能选择视图控制器
it only makes sense for this to be view controller.
Xcode 不能自动选择好 我真的很惊讶
And I’m really surprised the Xcode just doesn’t automatically do this.
我也不知道为什么
I’m not sure exactly why, because you –
这里选择 push 类型完全说不通
it would make no sense to pick push here,
那为什么还要给出这个选项 我不知道
so why even offer that. I don’t know.
总之选项卡栏控制器的 segue
Anyway, you always want to one on the bottom
要选择最下面的视图控制器
when it’s a tab bar controller,
表示将它连接到视图控制器列表中
which means wire this up to the list of view controllers.
这样做之后就会得到这样一条线
Okay. You do that and now it’s going to have this line drawn over there.
这些小圆圈不是 segue
Again, these little round circles are not segues,
视图控制器中
they’re showing the outlet view controllers,
它们是用来显示多个输出口视图控制器的
plural in the view controller case.
在分屏视图或者导航视图控制器中
It’s root view controller in the split view
这个位置显示的是根视图控制器
or the navigation view controller space over there.
我将它们连好了
So I got these things wired up.
注意 所有可能出现在这个选项卡栏中的场景
Note that on all of the scenes that might appear in this tab bar,
即使它们
even if they’re –
是通过导航控制器出现的
that’s happening through a navigation controller,
都会在底部留出这一栏的位置
they’re all getting room for this little bar on the bottom.
看到了吗
You see that?
底部的那条栏所占的空间
Little bar space on the bottom,
都会是这样
so that’s going to be true.
所以聪明的做法是
So it’s smart about knowing
确定某个场景是否最终出现在选项卡栏中
oh, this could eventually be in this tab bar,
然后提前在底部留出空间
so I’m going to make that space down there.
你同样需要调整 UI 以适应较小的空间
And again, you have to adjust your UI to fit in the smaller space, whatever.
注意 我们这里是将导航控制器放入选项卡栏控制器中
Notice we have a navigation controller inside a tab bar controller,
这是合法的
that’s legal,
反过来就不是了
other way around, not so much. Okay.
不要将选项卡栏控制器放入导航控制器中
Don’t be putting a tab bar controller inside a navigation controller.
请讲
Yeah?
怎么知道哪个选项卡会出现在左边呢
How do you know which one shows up on the left?
选项卡栏控制器
Well, the tab bar controller –
选项卡栏控制器所指向的 MVC
the things that the tab bar controller points to,
会出现在各个选项卡中
those are going to show up in each tab. Okay.
如果你将导航控制器连接到
If you wired from the navigation controller
某个有选项卡栏控制器的场景中
to any scene that had a tab bar controller in it,
就不对了
that would be bad.
所以基本上 选项卡栏控制器
So basically, the tab bar controller
不应该出现在导航控制器的下游
should not be anywhere downstream of a navigation controller.
但我的意思是…
Oh but, what I meant is…
问题是选项卡的顺序是什么
Oh, so the question is what’s the order of the tabs?
这是可以在 Xcode 中修改的
That can actually be changed in Xcode.
选项卡栏控制器底部会显示出各个选项卡
If you see where the tabs are in the bottom of the tab bar controller,
你可以拾取然后移动
you can pick those up and move them. Okay.
现在我们有了这两个选项卡
So anyway, so we have these two tabs.
我需要选择运行开始的位置
I’m going to make the launch point.
我要将箭头从导航控制器
I’m moving it from being the navigation controller
移到选项卡栏控制器上
over to be the tab bar controller. Right.
显然 我想在运行应用时让选项卡栏控制器
Obviously, I want the tab bar controller to be showing onscreen
首先出现在屏幕上
when it first launches,
可以在视图控制器底部双击
and I can double click down on a view controller
在那里修改标题文本
and change the text, right there.
看到所指的地方了吗 在那里双击
See where I am there? Double click.
还可以在右边设置图像
And I can also set the image over here on the right.
可以设置为资产库中的一张图像
You can set it to an image that’s in your assets library.
图像要求是 3030 像素的 Alpha 通道
These images need to be 30 by 30 pixels, all alpha. Okay.
也就是说 在 30*30 的图标中
In other words, your tint color is going to
你的色调颜色要通过 Alpha 通道显示出来
show through the alpha in that 30 by 30 icon.
就是这么简单
Okay. It’s as simple as that.
颜色要通过 Alpha 通道显示出来
It’s going to show through the alpha.
如果图标除了 Alpha 之外还有别的通道
So if that icon has anything but alpha in it,
比如不透明度 是不会显示出来的
you know, opaque and alpha, it’s not going to show. Okay.
就是这样了 就是这些
So that’s that. That’s it.
希望今天的内容能够帮助大家实现两种控制器
Hopefully that’s enough for you to do both kinds of controllers.
周五没有课外辅导
Friday, no section.
下周五帮助大家在设备上运行应用
Next Friday we’ll get you up and running on your devices.
周一没课
Monday, no lecture.
作业截止日期是周三 很方便
Your homework’s due on Wednesday, which is convenient,
从下周三开始
and then starting next week, next Wednesday
以及之后的两周
and for the two weeks after that,
我们会讲到绘制 手势 自动布局 动画
we’ll be doing drawing and gestures and autolayout animation.
很多有意思的内容
Lots and lots of fun stuff.
好的 非常感谢
Okay. Thank you very much.
更多内容 请访问斯坦福网站
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.